<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasons of the conversion of Mr. John Sidway from the Romish to the Protestant religion together with what usage he hath since received in the Church of England : as also a brief account of his travails / humbly communicated to the high court of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Sidway, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3770A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08781042</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08781042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1269:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasons of the conversion of Mr. John Sidway from the Romish to the Protestant religion together with what usage he hath since received in the Church of England : as also a brief account of his travails / humbly communicated to the high court of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Sidway, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 80 [i.e. 75] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nevil Simmons and Langley Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sidway, John.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REASONS OF THE CONVERSION OF Mr. John Sidway, FROM The <hi>Romiſh</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>Together with what uſage he hath ſince received in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo a brief Account of his Travails, Humbly Communicated to the High Court of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nevil Simmons,</hi> at the Three Golden Cocks, at the Weſt end of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>Langley Curtis</hi> on <hi>Ludgate</hi> Hill. 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41796:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH COURT OF PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>JOHN SIDWAY</hi> wiſheth Grace, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Peace, through Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat and manifold were the Bleſſings (moſt Noble and Magnificent Aſſembly) which Almighty God, the Father of all Mercies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the People of <hi>England,</hi> when your moſt Wiſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Anceſtors, by a moſt impartial
<pb facs="tcp:41796:3"/>and happy Reformation, expelled from the Church thoſe Thick and Palpable Clouds of darkneſs, that for many years had overshadowed this Land, And as it yet giveth unto all that are well affected an exceeding great cauſe of comfort, ſo the fruit thereof doth extend it ſelf, not only to the time ſpent in this Tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry World, but to our ſafe conduct to that Eternal Happineſs which is above in Heaven. The occaſions (moſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Aſſembly) of my relinquishing the <hi>Romiſh</hi> way of Worship, were the many exceeding groſs Errors, and moſt wicked Practices, which I found I muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be daily guilty of, continuing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And the Motives that enduced me to imbrace the Reformed Religion, and be Reconciled to <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> were the moſt Sacred Scriptures, and Antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, unto whom I found the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, both which, having here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited,
<pb facs="tcp:41796:3"/>I humbly Preſent to your High Court; Humbly craving (ſince things of this Nature, have ever been Subject to the cenſures of ill meaning, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented perſons) the ſame may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Approbation and Patronage from ſo Learned and Judicious an Aſſembly, as your High Court is; That ſo (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am expoſed hereby, on the one ſide, to the undeſerved Calumniations of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> party, who ſtrive to keep the World in ignorance and darkneſs; and, on the other ſide, to the Foolish Malignity of ſelf-conceited Brethren, who like of nothing but what is done by themſelves, or at leaſtwiſe framed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own fancy) I may reſt ſecure; ſupported within, by the Truth and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of a good Conſcience (having walked in the ways of Simplicity and Integrity, as before the Lord) and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained without, by the Powerful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb facs="tcp:41796:4"/>of your moſt Auguſt Aſſemblies, Grace and Favour (which no doubt will ever give Countenance to honeſt and Chriſtian endeavours) againſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cenſures, and Uncharitable Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>The Lord of Heaven and Earth grant to this our Nation, that by your wiſe endeavours, <hi>Popery</hi> may be utterly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated, and <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> firmly eſtablish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all generations: So that Peace and Happineſs, Truth and Juſtice, Religion and Piety, may ever flourish.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41796:4"/>
            <head>THE Printers Epiſtle TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince he that is Cured of a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Diſtemper, may do very good ſervice in Relating to others the means of his Recovery; The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath here exhibited to thy moſt Candid View, and Serious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, what (as may hereby eaſily be gathered) with very great Coſt, hard and diligent Study, long and tedious Travel, and moſt eminent Danger, he was ſeveral years in coming to the knowledge of.
<pb facs="tcp:41796:5"/>The Book (thou wilt find) although but little, is of very great and univerſal uſe. For (the Grace of God cooperating therewith) art thou a Heathen, Jew, Turk, or Infidel, it will bring thee to the Faith of Chriſt; art thou a Chriſtian, it will greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme thee in thy Sacred Faith, and exceedingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee in thy Religious Practice. More particularly, art thou a Papiſt, it will cauſe thee to Relinquiſh thy Errors, Idolatries, Blaſphemies, and Superſtitions, and to adhere to the moſt Catholick Faith, and moſt pure Practice of the Antient times. Art thou a Proteſtant, it will greatly fortifie and strengthen thee, in thy moſt Renowned Primitive Chriſtian Faith, and Orthodox Profeſsion. In fine, whatſoever thou art, it will bring thee to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Commands of God, and to avoid the Darts of the Devil; if thou reapeſt the benefit thereby intended, give God the Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41796:5"/>
            <p>WHereas there is joy in the Preſence of the Angels over a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Converted, and that we are Commanded to let our Light ſo ſhine before Men, as that they may ſee our good Works, and Glorify our father which is in Heaven; I have here ſhewed to the World, the Reaſons of my Converſion, from the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church. I was Born at <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> but of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Extract, was Educated in a Jeſuits Colledge at <hi>Bologna</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> where I remained until I had not only Commenced Maſter of Arts, but was by ſtanding Batchelor of Divinity. At my firſt coming to <hi>Bologna</hi> ſeveral Proteſtants often told me, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion was not good, and greatly indeavored to perſwade me from it, but perceiving their deſign herein was to bring me to their own, I deſired to know of them, whether the Proteſtant Religion were Catholick, had Antiquity, Succeſſion of Chairs, Perpetual continuance, wrought Miracles, and had the greateſt number of Chriſtians: (which I looked upon, being ſo inſtructed, to be the Marks of the true Church,) but they being not able to ſhew it to be thus in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſenſe, I was ſo obſtinate againſt Proteſtancy, that I gave them ſuch a repulſe they never after troubled me.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuits, in the next place, after I had been a while there, ſet upon me to enter into their order, and did ſo aſſault me with ſuch allurements and perſwaſions in order thereunto, that I was ſo ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to overcome their Temptations, that many a time I have ſpent all the time allotted for recreation, in Prayer to Almighty God, that of his great mercy he would give me his aſſiſtance to defend me from them. And as often as they tempted me thereunto, I told them, what I might have hereafter I knew not, but as yet I had no inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to enter into a Religious order; but if I had ever ſuch an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, I would ſooner enter into their order, then any other. And with this they ſeemed to be well ſatisfyed, nevertheleſs it was but a meer put off, for I did not at all approve their ways.</p>
            <p>When I came to ſtudy Divinity, reading the Fathers, I often in the ſame obſerved divers paſſages, which in my opinion, made as exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly againſt both the Faith and Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as might be, which whether they do or no, let the World Judge. I have quoted them exactly as they are in their works, making.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41796:6"/>
               <head>Firſt, againſt Purgatory <hi>&amp; Limbus Infantium.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe juſt are called to refreſhment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his Book of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, Sect. 11,</note> and the unjuſt are ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away to Puniſhment: there is preſently given rewards to the Faithful, and Puniſhments to the Wicked.</p>
               <p>The Faith of the Catholicks by Divine Authority believeth the firſt place to be the Kingdom of Heaven,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 7th Tomb, and 5th Book <hi>Hipognoſticôn</hi> againſt the <hi>Pelagians</hi> p. 957.</note> from whence, as I have ſaid, is excepted he which is not Baptized, the ſecond to be Hell; where every Apostate or Stranger from the Faith of Chriſt ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo Eternal Puniſhments. The third place we are utterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of, nor do we find it in the Holy Scriptures. Feign thou <hi>Pelagian 4.</hi> place out of the Ware-houſe of thy Opinion.</p>
               <p>Know for certain,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Book of the Vanity of the World, Tomb 9th Chap. 1.</note> that when the Soul is departed from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it is either preſently placed in Paradice for its good works, or certainly is caſt headlong into the Pit of Hell for its Sins. Chooſe you now what you will have, and diſpoſe of this now in your life-time, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perpetually to rejoyce with the Saints, or without end to be Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Wicked,</p>
               <p>Let no Man deceive himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 10th Tomb of time Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. 202.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo ſaith the ſame in Effect, in his 7th. Tomb and firſt Book of the Deſerts and Remiſſion of Sins, Chap. 28. And in his fifth Tomb and Twenty firſt Book of the City of God, Chap. 25.</p>
                  </note> my Brethren, there are but two places, and a third there is not for any, he which deſerveth not to Raign with Chriſt, without all douht ſhall Periſh with the Devil.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2ly. Againſt the Invocation of Angels and Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and the making of them our Mediators and Interceſſors.</head>
               <p>FOr it behoveth not the Church of God to leave off,<note place="margin">The Councel of <hi>Luodicea,</hi> can. 35.</note> and be gone, and nominate Angels, and make Congregations which are known to be forbidden; if any one therefore ſhall be found obſerving this Occult Idolatry, let him be accurſed, becauſe he leaveth our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the third Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s.</hi>
                  </note> and delivereth himſelf up to Idolatry.</p>
               <p>For whereas they did command to adore Angels, he commanded the contrary, that both words and deeds might adorn the remembrance of Chriſt the Lord: and ſaith through the ſending forth of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41796:7"/>of thanksgiving to God and the Father,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clement</hi> Pope and Martyr in his ſecond Book of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions c. 32.</note> by him, and not by Angels. Following alſo this Law of the <hi>Laodicean</hi> Councel, and willing to be cured of that old Diſeaſe, read, it is to be taken heed leaſt they ſhould pray to Augels, and leaſt they ſhould leave Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>It is not lawful to come to Almighty God, unleſs by Christ.</p>
               <p>And whereas notwithſtanding he ſaith to us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Origin</hi> in his Bighth Book againſt <hi>Celſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> there is one God the Father of whom are all things, he ſaith to us this word of himſelf, and to all which would aſcend to the moſt High God of Gods, and to the moſt High Lord of Lords, but he aſcendeth to the most High God, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably and indiviſibly Worſhippeth him, by Jeſus the Son of God; by whoſe only conduct he cometh to the Father.</p>
               <p>He hath ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril</hi> in his Eleventh Book upon <hi>John.</hi> c. 7.</note> impelling them to ask with confidence, affirming <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen,</hi> whatſoever you ſhall obtain by requeſt from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you ſhall ask it in my name, and hath added in my name to the end he may ſhew himſelf a Mediator, for no Man cometh to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſs by the Son.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Athanaſius</hi> alſo in his Fourth Oration againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> treating upon the words of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> pag. 259. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Eighth Tomb, in his Enarration of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>undred and Eighth Pſalm, ſay plainly the like things.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>3ly. Againſt one Mans works being applyed to another.</head>
               <p>FOr the fooliſh Virgins,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilary</hi> in his Commentary upon <hi>Matthew,</hi> Cannon. 27.</note> their Lamps being out, cannot go forth to meet him. They which were Wiſe were Prayed that they would lend them Oyle; to whom they anſwered we cannot lend our ſelves, becauſe there is not perhaps that there may be enough for every one. So that works and deſerts done by others ſhall help no Man, becauſe it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that every one buy Oyle for his own Lamp.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Leo</hi> the Great in his 81 Epiſtle, which is to the <hi>Paleſtine Monks,</hi> in the firſt Tomb of the Councels, pag 791. And <hi>Leo</hi> the Pope in his 95 Epiſtle written to <hi>Leo Auguſtus,</hi> do plainly alſo ſay the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41796:8"/>
               <head>Fourthly. Againſt the Adoration of Angels, Martyrs, and Saints departed.</head>
               <p>LEt <hi>Mary</hi> be had in honor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his third Book, Haereſ. 79.</note> and the Father the Son and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt be Adored: <hi>Mary</hi> no Body Adoreth. I ſay not that either Woman or Man, neither do the Angels receive ſuch glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this Myſtery is due to God. The things which were ill writ in the Heart of the deceiver are blotted out. The deſire of the Tree is taken from the Eyes, it is turned again a fiction to the Lord. <hi>Eve</hi> returned with <hi>Adam,</hi> that ſhe might Worſhip God only; not that ſhe might be led away by the voice of the Serpent, but might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Precept of God, thou ſhalt not Eat of the Tree; and it was a Tree, not error, but by him the Tree was made inobedience of Error. Let not any one Eat of the Error, which is for St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> ſake, for although the Tree was fair, but yet not for Food; ſo <hi>Mary</hi> is very fair, and holy, and honorable; but not for Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Theſe truly do again renew the mixture of Fortune and prepare a Table for the Devil and not for God, as it is written, and they are fed with the food of impiety, and as the holy Scripture ſaith, and the Women do bear fine Flower, and their Children ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wood, to make Cakes with Oyle ſubdued to the Army of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Such Women are repreſſed by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> that they may not trouble the World; and leſt they ſhould ſay, let us honor the Queen of Heaven.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> in his Third Tomb and Sixth Book againſt <hi>Julian</hi> fol. 50 in the Letter A.</note> 
                  <hi>Taphnas</hi> alſo knew to Puniſh theſe; the places of theſe Edifices have known to receive Bodies to Corruption.</p>
               <p>But we ſay the Holy Martyrs be neither Gods, nor have we been wont to Adore them: But we Praiſe them with reat Honors that they have ſtriven valiantly for the truth, and have obſerved the ſincerity of Faith, ſo that they deſpiſed their lives, and their fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel ſayings prevailed in the greateſt Perils by the Terrors of Death; and were of ſuch fortitude, as to ſtir up to themſelves Statues of their life.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41796:9"/>
               <p>I do not ſay that we may not Worſhip and Adore the reliques of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierom</hi> in his ſecond Tomb in his Epiſtle againſt <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> for the repair of the Prieſts. p. 119.</note> but alſo that we may not Worſhip and Adore the Sun and Moon, not Angels, not Arch-Angels, not Cherubin, not Seraphin, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny name which is named both in this World and in the World to come, for we may not ſerve Creatures rather than the Creator, which is Bleſſed in the World.</p>
               <p>The Worſhip of dead Men is not a Religion for us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his firſt Tomb in his Book of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, chap. 55.</note> if they have lived God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily, they have no ſuch property as to ſeek ſuch honors; but they will worſhip him, by whoſe illumination their deſerts are Praiſed by us that we be their Fellow-ſervants, therefore they are to be honored for imitations ſake, not for Religions ſake, but if they have lived all, whereſoever they are, they are not ſo to be honored.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo in his firſt Tomb, in his Book of the Manners of the Catholick Church chap. 30. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in his ſecond Book of Treaſure, in his firſt chapter againſt <hi>Eunomius; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros</hi> in his firſt Book of Faith to <hi>Gratianus Auguſtus,</hi> chap. 7. and many others, do ſay the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fifthly. Againſt the Adoration of Images.</head>
               <p>IT pleaſeth,<note place="margin">The Councel of <hi>Eliber</hi> cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great. Can. 36. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Book of the Crown of a Warrier, c. 10.</note> that Pictures ought not to be in the Church, nor that any thing ſhould be Painted upon the Walls, leaſt the ſame ſhould be Worſhipped and Adored.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> the leſs hath ſaid, keep you from Idols; not now from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as from a duty; but from Idols: that is, from the very Effigies of them, for it is an unworthy thing that there ſhould be an Image of the Living God, an Image of an Idol and dead thing there may be.</p>
               <p>It is not to be doubted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his ſecond Book of Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions c. 19.</note> but there is no Religion, where there is an Image, for if Religion be of Divine things, there is nothing Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine unleſs in Celeſtial things. Images therefore want Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that nothing Celeſtial can be in that thing, which is made of the Earth; which truly may appear to a Wiſe-man by the very name, for whatſoever is feigned, muſt needs be falſe; neither may that ever receive the name of a true thing, which feigneth the truth like a Drone, and for imitation, but if there be any imitation, it is not chiefly a ſerious thing, but is as it were a Play and a Jeſt. Religion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41796:10"/>is not in Images, but in Images is the least of Religion. The true one therefore is to be preferred before the falſe, and we muſt tread under foot Earthly things, that we may follow Heavenly.</p>
               <p>Take heed to your ſelves, that you obſerve the Traditions which you have received,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphanius Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prius,</hi> as he is Cited by <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Neocaeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſi</hi> in the ſixt action of the ſecond <hi>Nicen</hi> Councel</note> that you do not decline either to the right hand, or to the left; for the doing of which bear away theſe things: Be you mindful, my beloved Children, that you do not carry Images in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, nor ſet them in the Burial places of the Saints, but perpetually carry about you God in your Hearts. Moreover do not ſuffer them in your common houſe, for it is not a Chriſtian right to he held ſuſpended by the Eyes, but by the Cogitation of the Mind.</p>
               <p>God forbiddeth an Idol as well to be made, as to be worſhipped, and by how much it goeth before, that it may be that which may be worſhipped;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Book of Idolatry, <hi>ch.</hi> 4.</note> by ſo much it is before, that it may not be, if it be not lawful to be worſhipped. For this cauſe, the Divine Law Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the very matter, <hi>to wit,</hi> of Idolatry to be rooted out, you ſhall not make (ſaith the ſame) an Idol adjoyning, neither the likeneſs of them which are in Heaven, and which are in Earth, and which are in the Sea: and ſtrictly forbiddeth the Servants of God, the Arts of this ſort throughout the whole world. <hi>Enoch</hi> alſo had gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foretelling this, that all the Elements, and every Senſe of the World, which are contained in Heaven, which are contained in the Sea, and which are contained in the Earth, ſhould be turned Devils unto Idolatry; and that the Spirits of Deſert Angels ſhould be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated for God against the Lord. Every thing therefore that a humane worſhippeth beſides him, who is the Maker and Creator of all things, is an error; their Images are Idols, and the Conſecration of Images is Idolatry, whatſoever a worſhipper of Images commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, without doubt it ſhall be deputed to whatſoever Artificer and of whatſoever Idol. Laſtly, the ſaid <hi>Enoch</hi> precondemneth in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, both the makers and worſhippers of an Idol.</p>
               <p>I ſwear to you Sinners,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the ſame place.</note> that in the day of the Blood of Perdition, there is prepared a Penance for you, you which ſerve ſtones, and which make Golden, Silver, Wooden and Stony Images, and Fictils, and ſerve Phantaſmes, and Devils, and infamous Spirits, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry error not according to knowledge, ſhall find no help from them.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41796:11"/>
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> truly ſaith, be you witneſſes if there be a God beſides me. And there were not then, which do counterfeit and carve out every vain thing which they make at their pleaſure, which cannot profit them. And afterward that whole ſaying deteſteth as well againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers as the worſhippers, whoſe clauſe it is: Know you that the heart of them is Aſhes, and they erre, and not one of them can deliver his own Soul. When <hi>David</hi> alſo ſaith the like, and ſuch are they become which make them, but what do I a Man of a mean Memory ſhew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what I can reckon up, or what I can recollect of the Scriptures, as though a word of the Holy Ghoſt may not be ſufficient, or beyond what may be deliberated, whether the Lord will Curſe and Condemn them, in the firſt place the makers of them, the Worſhippers of whom he Curſeth and Condemneth.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his Dialogue with <hi>Tryphon</hi> a Jew. pag. <hi>251. Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in his Oration adhortory to the Gentils, pag. <hi>25.</hi> of the Latin florentine Edition. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Scorpiaco</hi> againſt the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> chap. <hi>2.</hi> And many others alſo ſay the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>6ly. Againſt the Adoration of Holy Reliques.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierome</hi> in the Epiſtle to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parius</hi> againſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> in his ſecond Tomb folio 119. and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. <hi>Vigilantius</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Hierome</hi> a Holy Prieſt in his 1ſt Tomb in the Epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> follo 106. which alſo <hi>Caeſar Baronius</hi> confeſſeth A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: Eccl. Tomb 5. in the year of our Lord 406. thus writeth as it is quoted by <hi>Hierome</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Tomb, in his Epiſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, fol. 123.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> do not ſay that we may not Worſhip and Adore the Reliques of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, but alſo that we may not Worſhip and Adore the Sun and Moon, not Angels, not Archangels, not Cherubim, not Seraphim, nor any Name which is Named both in this World and the World to come, for we may not ſerve Creatures rather than the Creator, which is Bleſſed in the World.</p>
               <p>What need is there, that thou with ſo much honor, not only doſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, but alſo Adore, that which is I know not what, which bearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in a little Veſsel thou Worſhippeſt?<note n="*" place="margin">in the ſame Book alſo.</note> What Duſt incloſed in Linnen, Adoring doeſt thou Kiſs?<note n="†" place="margin">And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> We ſeem near to the cuſtome of the Gentils to introduce in the Churches under the pretence of Religion, the Sun as yet Shining, whole heaps of waxen things to be lighted: and whereſoever there is I know not what duſt, in a little precious Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel incloſed in Linnen, the Kiſſers thereof do Adore it. Men ſhew great Honor of this ſort to the Bleſſed Martyrs, whom they think
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41796:12"/>to be illuſtrated by the most vile waxen lights: and whom the Lamb, which is in the midſt of the Throne, with every ray of his Majeſty illuſtrateth.<note place="bottom">The Councel of <hi>Eliber</hi> alſo; celebrated in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, in its 34 and 35 Cannon ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>7ly. Againſt Tranſubſtantiation, and by Conſequence, the Adoration of the Hoſt.</head>
               <p>THe Lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, Dialog. firſt.</note> when he had taken the Symbal or Sign, ſaid not, this is my Deity, but this is my Body.</p>
               <p>He gave to his Diſciples the Image,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Procopius Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus,</hi> upon the 49 Chapter of the Book of <hi>G.</hi>
                  </note> Effigies, or Tipe of his Body, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, as thou mayeſt gather, not any thing further of raw and bloody Sacrifices.</p>
               <p>Bread being taken and diſtributed to the Diſciples, he made it his Body,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Fourth Book againſt Marcione, c. 19</note> ſaying this is my Body, that is, the Figure of my Body. And it could not have been a Figure, unleſs the Body were of verity, for it is an empty thing, which is a Phantaſme, that cannot take a Figure.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt ſaith;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his fourth Book of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, chap. 5.</note> make this oblation aſcribed to us, rational and acceptable, which is the Figure of the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Lord admitted <hi>Judas</hi> to the Banquet in which he commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and delivered to his Diſciples the Figure of his Body and Blood.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the third Pſalm.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Look into the ſame diligently,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephrem Syrus</hi> to them which will ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the nature of the Son of God. chap. 4.</note> how taking in his hands the Bread, he Bleſſed it and Brake it for a Figure of his Immaculate Body; and the Cup he Bleſſed and gave to his Diſciples for a Figure of his Precious Blood.<note place="bottom">Alſ <hi>Charles</hi> the Great in his Epiſtle to <hi>Alcuinus</hi> of the Reaſon of Sept. in his Book of Divine Offices; <hi>Bertramus</hi> of the Supper of the Lord; <hi>Origines</hi> againſt the <hi>Marcionits</hi> Diolog. 3. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his Eighty third Homily upon <hi>Matthew;</hi> and many others, ſay in ſenſe the ſame.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41796:13"/>
               <head>Eighthly, Againſt the Adoration of the Altar, the Croſs, and all manner of Creatures, whether of Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or of Mans Invention.</head>
               <p>THE Catholick Church the true Mother of Chriſtians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the firſt Tome, in his Book of the Manners of the Church Catholick, ch. 30.</note> doth not only deſervedly Preach that God himſelf, whoſe adoption is a most bleſſed life, is moſt Purely and moſt Chaſtly to be Worſhipped, but we command that no Creature to be Adored be brought in, for us to ſerve the ſame; and by that uncorrupt and inviolable Eternity, to only whom Man is Subject, and to only whom the rational Soul in not cohering is miſerable: Excluding every thing that is made, that is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to change, and is Subject to the time.<note place="bottom">The like alſo affirmeth <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his Second Book againſt <hi>Origen Adamurtius</hi> in the 64 Hereſie, pag 231.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ninthly, Againſt Prayer for the Dead.</head>
               <p>READ the Scriptures of our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his twenty Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Homily to the people of <hi>Antioch. Hierome</hi> in his Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon the Sixth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans</hi> on theſe words, every one ſhall bear his own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</note> and learn how we wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hither and thither can help no body, not a Brother redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Brother from interminable torments: not a Friend, a Friend; not the Parents their Children; nor the Children their Parents; but why do I ſpeak of miſerable men, when neither if <hi>Noah</hi> cometh, and <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> then judging can Pray us out.</p>
               <p>Whilſt we are in this preſent world, either by Prayers or Counſels we may be helpful to our neighbour, but when we ſhall come before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal of Chriſt, not <hi>Job,</hi> not <hi>Daniel,</hi> neither <hi>Noah</hi> can ask for any one; but every one ſhall bear his own burthen.<note place="bottom">The ſame in ſenſe ſaith alſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Tenth Tome, in the thirty Second Sermon of the words of the Apoſtle.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41796:14"/>
               <head>Tenthly. Againſt humane merit.</head>
               <p>THe forgiveneſs of Sins is not the merit of Honeſty,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilarie</hi> in his Enerration upon the 66. <hi>Pſalm</hi> near the beginning. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the ninth Book of his Moral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 11. <hi>Bernard</hi> in his Treatiſe of Grace &amp; Free will, not far from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</note> but the will of a free indulgence from the riches of goodneſs, a gift abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pitty.</p>
               <p>Although I ſhould abound for the work of virtue, I attain to Life, not by merit but by pardon.</p>
               <p>Where therefore, ſaith he, are our merits? or where is our hope? Hear I ſay, not by works of Juſtice which we have done, but according to his mercy he hath ſaved us. Why therefore doſt thou reſolutely think that thou haſt created thy merits, and canſt be ſaved by thy own Righteouſneſs, which canſt not ſo much as ſay the Lord Jeſus, unleſs in the Holy Ghoſt? haſt thou indeed forgotten he which hath ſaid, without me you can do nothing? and that it is neither of the runner, nor of the willer, but of God ſhewing mercy?<note place="bottom">The ſame alſo in effect, ſaith <hi>Hilary</hi> in his Sermon upon the 51. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> not far from the end.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eleventhly. Againſt Auricular Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Do not lead thee upon the Stage of thy aſſociates,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his ſecond Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily upon the 50. <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
                  </note> I do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel thee to diſcover thy Sins to Men: rehearſe and unfold thy Conſcience before God. Shew to the Lord the moſt excellent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian thy wounds, and ask of him a Medicament. Shew them to him who not in the least reproacheth, but moſt graciouſly cureth.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41796:15"/>
               <p>What therefore have I to do with Men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his firſt tome &amp; tenth Book of Confeſſions <hi>chap.</hi> 3.</note> that they ſhould hear my Confeſſions, and as if they could heal all my griefs? A curious kind of people to know anothers life, but ſlothful to correct their own life. Why do they inquire of me to hear what I am, who will not that thou my God do hear what they are? and from whence know they, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by my ſelf, they hear from my ſelf; or whether I ſay true or no, ſeeing that no one knoweth what is done of Men towards Man, unleſs the Spirit of Man which is in himſelf.<note place="bottom">The ſame alſo in effect, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 31. <hi>Homily</hi> upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the which is upon the 12. <hi>chap. Pag.</hi> 1956. according to the Commelinian Edition.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Twelfthly. Againſt Humane Satisfaction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter</hi> grieved and wept,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon the 22. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Luke.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe he erred as a Man. I find not what he ſaid; I find that he wept; I read of his Tears, but I read not of his ſatisfaction.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his ninth tome in his ſecond Treatiſe upon the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Sins are forgiven you by his name, and not by the name of any Man, or of any thing of Man.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> in effect alſo, ſaith the ſame in his Sermon of waſhing the Feet, in the laſt Section.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Thirteenthly. Againſt Pilgrimages.</head>
               <p>NOt that we have been at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linus</hi> about the Inſtitution of a Monk, tom. 1. fol. 103.</note> but that we have lived well at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is to be praiſed, that City is to be wiſhed for, not which hath killed the Prophets, and poured forth the Blood of Chriſt, but which the violence of a River maketh glad, which being Scituated upon a Mountain cannot be hid: which an Apoſtle proclaimeth to be the Mother of the Saints; and in which there is gladneſs that it ſelf
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41796:16"/>hath a freedom with the Saints. I do not, in ſaying this, reprove my ſelf of inconſtancy, or condemn what I do, or that I may ſeem to have left both mine and my Country (after the Example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>) in vain, but I dare not confine the Omnipotency of God in a ſtrait corner, and keep it in a little place of the Earth which containeth not Heaven, for each one of the Believers are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by the diverſities of places, but by the merit of Faith. And the true Adorers, neither at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> nor on Mount <hi>Gazarim</hi> do Adore the Father; for God is a Spirit, and his Adorers ought to Adore him in Spirit and in Truth, the Spirit Breatheth where it liſteth: The Earth is the Lords and the fulneſs thereof. After that the whole World was watered with Celeſtial dew, and made dry by the fall of the Jew, many coming both from the Eaſt and the Weſt, ſate down in the Boſome of <hi>Abraham.</hi> It is to be noted, that God ceaſed in <hi>Judea,</hi> and his great Name in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but into every Nation went forth the ſound of the Apoſtles, and their words unto the Ends of the Earth. Our Saviour ſpeaking to his Diſciples when he was in the Temple: Said ariſe, let us go hence, and to the <hi>Jews</hi> your houſe ſhall be left to you deſolate, if Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, verily all things which are Earthly ſhall paſs away. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both the Croſs and the place of Reſurrection are profitable to thoſe, which bear their Croſs; and riſe dayly with Chriſt; and ſhew themſelves worthy for ſuch a Habitation. But they which ſay, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, let them hear from the Apoſtle, you are the Temple of the Lord, and the Holy Ghost inhabiteth in you. Both at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and at <hi>Britain,</hi> the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Court is equally open; for the Kingdom of God is within you. Examine <hi>Anthony,</hi> and all the Monks of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of <hi>Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> of <hi>Pontus,</hi> of <hi>Capadocia,</hi> and of <hi>Armenia,</hi> and they have not ſeen <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and it is manifeſt to them that without this City is the Gate of Paradiſe. Bleſsed <hi>Hilarion,</hi> when <hi>Paleſtina</hi> was, and he lived in <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> one only day ſaw <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that he might ſeem neither to contemn the Holy Place for its neerneſs, nor again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the Lord in a Place.</p>
               <p>Towards what place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierome</hi> in the ſame place, a little after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</note> canſt thou ſay, that theſe things were reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from a long beginning; ſurely thou doſt not think that any thing of thy Faith is wanting, becauſe thou haſt not ſeen <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> neither do we therefore eſteem our ſelves the better, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41796:17"/>the Habitation of this place; but whether here or elſewhere, thou haſt an equal reward by our Lord for thy works.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Claudius Taurinenſis</hi> a Biſhop of the Church againſt <hi>Theodemirus Abbot,</hi> concerning Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage for Religion ſake to the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> in his fifth Tomb of Orthodox writing referred to <hi>Jonah</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aurelianenſis</hi> in the third Book of the Worſhip of Images, pag. 1570. Saith plainly alſo the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>14ly. Againſt Sacrifice.</head>
               <p>HE did not ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt ch. of <hi>John, Homil.</hi> 17. of the words of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, behold the Lamb of God he which taketh away the Sins of the World.</note> which ſhall take away, or hath took away; but which taketh away the Sins of the World, that he may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood dayly to take away the ſame, for not only when he Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed did he take away our Sins, but from that time hitherto he tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them away; he is not always Crucified, for he offered for our Sins one Sacrifice, but always by that one he Purgeth us.</p>
               <p>He hath, indeed, by his Death, that one true Sacrifice offered for us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his third Tomb and fourth Book of the trinity, ch. 13.</note> purged, aboliſhed, and extinguiſhed, whatſoever there was of faults wherewith Principalities and Powers did detain us by the Law for to pay Puniſhments; and by his Reſurrection unto a new life hath called us that are predeſtinated, hath juſtiſied us that are called, and hath glorified us that are juſtified.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo in his <hi>Enchiridium</hi> to <hi>Laurentius,</hi> chap. 62. Plainly ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>15ly. Againſt St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s being the Head of the Apoſtles, and the Pope's being the Head of the Church.</head>
               <p>THis truly which was Peter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> the Martyr in his Book of the Unity of the Church S. 3.</note> and the other Apoſtles, were endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an Equal conſort both of Honor and Power.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41796:18"/>
               <p>Chriſt after his Reſurrection gave to all his Apoſtles an equal Power.<note place="margin">In the ſame a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ittle before.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoever hath deſired Primacy on Earth,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome in his forty third Homily of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect works upon the twenty third Chapter of <hi>Matthew.</hi>
                  </note> ſhall find confuſion in Heaven; neither ſhall he be accounted amongst the Servants of Chriſt, that treats of Primacy.</p>
               <p>Whereſoever a Biſhop ſhall be, whether at <hi>Rome,</hi> or at <hi>Eugubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or at <hi>Regium,</hi> or at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> or at <hi>Tanis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hierome in his Epiſtle to <hi>Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grins.</hi>
                  </note> he is both of the ſame merit, and of the ſame Prieſthood. The power of Riches, and humility of Poverty, or loftineſs, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority, maketh not a Biſhop: but they are all the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>None of the Patriarchs ever uſed univerſal in his denomination,<note place="margin">Pelagius the ſecond, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in his Epiſtle to all the Biſhops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully called together by <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi>
                  </note> for if any one Patriarch be ſaid to be univerſal, the name of the rest of the Patriarchs is diminiſhed. But bet his far from us, let the faithful of whatſoever kind be far from the mind that any one ſhould ſnatch or covet to himſelf this, from whence it may ſeem that the honor of their Brothers, (by how little or ſmall a part ſoever) is diminiſhed. Wherefore your charity no Man ever nameth in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles univerſal, leſt he diminiſh to himſelf a debt, ſeeing he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon another a honor being not due.</p>
               <p>Let that name of Blaſphemy be far from the hearts of Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Gregory the Great in his fourth Book of Epiſtles from the Regiſter, Epiſt. <hi>32.</hi> which is to <hi>Mauricius Auguſtus.</hi>
                  </note> in which the honor of all the Prieſts is taken away, whilſt it is mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arrogated by one to himſelf.<note place="bottom">Chryſoſtome upon the firſt chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles; and Gregory the Great, in the fourth Book of the Epiſtles from the Regiſter, Epiſtle <hi>34.</hi> which is to Conſtantia Auguſta, do clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo ſay the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41796:19"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>16ly. Againſt the Roman Churches infallibility.</head>
               <p>AFter ſo many benefits they turned the Priviledges of Dignity into contempt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the ſecond c. of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> thus inveheth againſt the Prieſts of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> inſomuch as the Prieſts of the Lord were idle, ſo that the Doctors of the Law were ignorant of him, which they ought to have taught to others, and the Paſtors through negligence became deceivers, and the Prophets which diſputed among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, did not ſpeak to God, but an Idol; and Worſhipped their own fiction. And we might uſe theſe words againſt the Maſters of our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which devour the People of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierom</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Orders of the Church, c. 5. as it is cited in the Cannon Law diſtinct. 93. in the chap. of a Deacon which in order is the 23.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now by whom in the Churches, as in the Romane Empire, Covetouſneſs hath increaſed, the Law of the Prieſt and the Viſion of the Prophet hath Periſhed. Every one truly by the Power of an Epiſcopal name, which they maintain to themſelves unlawfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, do bring back by force unto their own uſes, all which is of the Levites; neither do they maintain to themſelves that which is written, but take away the whole from all.</p>
               <p>At that ſame time in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his fifth Book of his Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick Hiſtory, chap. 20.</note> they were greatly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed with divers novelties by the many Eccleſiaſtick rules of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Hierom</hi> alſo to <hi>Evagrius</hi> the Biſhop in the 85 Epiſtle, in the ſecond Tome, and as it is cited in the Cannon Law, in the ſame diſtinction aboveſaid, in the Chapter that is in order the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fourth, plainly ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>17ly. Againſt Papal Diſpenſations.</head>
               <p>THat is not able to ſtand,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gratianus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick. chap. 8.</note> which is done againſt the Evangelical or Prophetical Doctrine or Conſtitution.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41796:20"/>
               <p>Neither ſhall any thing ſtand,<note place="margin">Pope <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle.</note> although it hath been acted by the Holy Fathers, that is constituted againſt the Evangelical or Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, or Apoſtolical Doctrine.</p>
               <p>It is not in the Power of the Pope,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gerſon</hi> of the Spiritual life of the Soul.</note> or of a Councel, or of the Church, to change the traditions given by the Evangeliſts and by <hi>Paul,</hi> as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſons dote.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Urbanus</hi> the Pope, as he is cited in the Cannon Law, in the Twenty fifth cauſe, plainly alſo ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>18ly. Againſt Multitude of Ceremonies.</head>
               <p>THis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierome</hi> in his commentaries upon the 23d. Chap. of <hi>Mat. Peter de Aliacp.</hi> Cardinal, Chamberlain of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church and Prelates.</note> even to this very day with us, both at the little Goſpels, and to the word of the Croſs, and to things of this ſort, do the Superſtitious Women practice; who have indeed a zeal of God but not according to knowledge; ſtraining at a Gnat, and ſwallowing a Camel.</p>
               <p>It were to be taken care of, that in Divine Service there were not ſuch a burthenſome length, but that there ſhould be obſerved a wiſhed and innocent brevity.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>John Gerſon</hi> alſo in the third part of the works of the Spiritual life of the Soul, in the ſecond Leſſon, plainly ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41796:21"/>
               <head>19ly. Againſt an Obligation to a Single life, either in Prieſt's, or others.</head>
               <p>ANdrightly hath <hi>(Paul)</hi> put that,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret</hi> up on the fourth chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy.</hi>
                  </note> forbidding to Marry; for he doth not diſpraiſe continency and a ſingle life, but accuſeth them which by a made Law do compel to follow the ſame.</p>
               <p>Integrity of the Body is to be wiſhed by you;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Book of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity, as it is cited in the Cannon Law, cauſ. 32. Qu. 2. in the c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, which is in number the thirteenth. The fifth Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</note> which I for counſel perſwade, nor for Empire command, for Virginity is alone, which may be perſwaded, but not commanded; a thing rather to be wiſhed then to be enjoyned.</p>
               <p>A Biſhop, or a Prieſt, or Deacon ſhall not under the pretence of Religion put away his proper Wife, and if he reject her let him be Excommunicated, but if he ſo perſevere, let him be caſt out.</p>
               <p>That in his time very many Prieſts were Married,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierome</hi> in his firſt Tome of Epiſtles, and firſt Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Jovini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, pag 33. teſtifieth.</note> and that a Biſhop is deſcribed by the Apoſtle to be the Husband of one Wife, having his Children with all Chaſtity.</p>
               <p>It is neither proved by reaſon or Authority, that abſolutely ſpeaking, a Prieſt can ſin by being Married;<note place="margin">Cardinal <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan</hi> in opuſe. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. Tract. 27 And in the ſame place a little after he concludeth.</note> neither is an order, in as much as it is an order; nor an order in as much as it is holy an impediment to Matrimony.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41796:22"/>
               <p>The Prieſt-hood not to break off the contract of Matrimony, whether it be before or after Ordination, is ſecluded by all Laws, ſtanding only in thoſe which we have from Chriſt and his Apoſtles.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Clement,</hi> a Roman, the Diſciple of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, and (as the Papiſts will have it) his Succeſſor in the Roman Biſhoprick, in his ſecond Book of Apoſtolical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, chap. 2. deſcribing of what ſort a Biſhop ought to be, plainly alſo ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>20ly. That the Holy Scriptures are the only Rule both of our Faith and Actions.</head>
               <p>GOd Gave a Law to us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the 8. chapter of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> v. 20.</note> and the Teſtimonies of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which if you will not follow, you will not have light, but darkneſs will always oppreſs you.</p>
               <p>As the night extinguiſheth not the Stars of Heaven:<note place="margin">Pope <hi>Zepheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to the Biſhops of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia,</hi> as it is ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Cannon Law, Diſtinct 38. in the chapter Sicut, which is in order the Eighth.</note>So Worldly iniquity obſcureth not the Minds of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, adhering to the Firmament of the Holy Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41796:23"/>
               <p>The Gentile ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Homil</hi> 33.</note> I would be a Chriſtian, but I know not to what to adhere, many quarrels are among you, I know not what Opinion I may chooſe. Every one ſaith, I ſay true; I know not who I may believe, ſeeing that on all ſides they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Scriptures. I anſwer them; this makes greatly for us. For if we ought to ſay that we believe reaſons, thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly troubled: But ſeeing we receive the Scriptures, and that they are both ſimple and true, it will be caſie for thee to Judge If any one conſenteth to theſe, he is a Chriſtian; if any one be againſt them, he is far from this Cannon.</p>
               <p>There is not any other left for the Speeches of Men concerning the things of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilary</hi> in his ſeventh Book of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> pag. 125.</note> ſaving only the Word of God.</p>
               <p>It behoveth us to confirm every word or thing by a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Holy Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> the great in his twenty Sixth Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of Morals, chap. 1.</note> both for the certainty and perfection of good, and confuſion of evil.</p>
               <p>The Scripture Divinely inſpired is conſtituted an Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor for us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> the great in his Book of Epiſtles, Epiſt, 80. which is to <hi>Euſtathius</hi> the Phyſitian. p. 714. accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benian Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Printed in the year 1566.</note> and by whom there ſhall be found agreeable Edicts in Divine words, even to theſe and no more approacheth a Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of verity.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the Seventh Tome, in his Book of the unity of the Church, c. 16. plainly alſo ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41796:24"/>
               <head>21ly. That the Scriptures contain what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Doctrine is neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>THe Goſpel containeth all things both for the preſent and the future,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Titus, Homil.</hi> 1.</note> and in a word hath wrapt therein honor and Piety, and Faith, and alſo every thing of Preaching.</p>
               <p>Not all things which God did,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> in his twelfth Book upon <hi>John</hi> chap. the laſt.</note> are written; but thoſe which are written as well for Manners as Belief are Judged to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that by a right faith and Works we may come Shining to the Kingdom of Heaven by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For all the Scripture,<note place="margin">Cardinal <hi>Hugo</hi> of St. <hi>Charo ia Poſtilla</hi> upon 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> that is the Holy Scripture which is concerning all things neceſsary to Salvation, and which is all the whole, that is, Perfect, and therefore priviledgeth the Name of Scripture to it ſelf by putting one Name for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>The Speech is of the Sacred Letters of the old Teſtament,<note place="margin">Cardinal <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan</hi> upon 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> which can inſtruct and teach thee, as touching wiſdome, unto Salvation
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41796:25"/>by Faith; for they have the faculty of teaching the Wiſdom, not of this World, but unto Eternal Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as touching the whole, and conſiſting of all things requiſite unto the perfecting of the Man of God.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Lord Jeſus hath done many things,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his ninth tome, and forty ninth Treatiſe upon <hi>John.</hi>
                  </note> not all have been written; but they are choice ones which were written, which ſeemed to ſuffice Believers to Salvation.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his twenty ſecond Chapter againſt <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> and in his Book of the Fleſh of Chriſt, chap. 7. plainly alſo ſaith the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>22. That God only ought to be Adored and Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</head>
               <p>ONly God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen</hi> in his eighth Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Celſus.</hi>
                  </note> who is the best and greateſt, is to be Adored; and Prayers are to be offered by the only begotten Word of God alone.</p>
               <p>To God alone by Jeſus offer Prayers.<note place="margin">And in the ſame a little afterward.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For we have learned to Adore only him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his fourth Book of Evangelical preparation chap. 5.</note> who is the God and Creator of all things.</p>
               <p>Neither do we read that any thing is to be Adored beſides God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his third Book of the holy Ghoſt chap. 12.</note> for it is written, thou ſhalt Adore the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41796:26"/>
               <p>But nevertheleſs thou O Lord art only to be Adored,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his prayer at the departure of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> Fol. 137. in the letter 6.</note> thou only art to be asked, that he (<hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Great, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) may be with his Sons brought in thy preſence.</p>
               <p>He truly conſerveth verity,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> in his twelfth Book of Treaſure, chap. 1.</note> which contrarily, not the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the Creator worſhippeth, and him only Serveth.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrium</hi> as he is reheatſed by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his ſeventh Book of the Hiſtory of the Church, chap. 10. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the firſt tome of his Book of the true Religion, chap. 55. plainly alſo ſay the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>23. That the Pope is Antichriſt.</head>
               <p>WHat is this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arnulph</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Orleans</hi> in a Councel Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Rhemes</hi> under the King the Head, in which <hi>Arnulph</hi> was appointed Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> ſpeaketh thus of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> This Speech alſo the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel never contradicted, but then judged according to the opinion of <hi>Arnulph</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> as it is recited in the tenth Century of the Hiſtory of <hi>Magdeburge,</hi> Printed at <hi>Baſil.</hi>
                  </note> Moſt Reverend Fathers, what is this Man Sitting in a lofty Throne, ſhining with Gold and a Purple Veſtment, what, I ſay, do you believe that this Man is? It is no wonder if he be deſtitute of the Love of God, and be proud with the only Wiſdome alſo taken from him, for he is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſitting in the Temple of Cod, and ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</p>
               <p>I being compelled to <hi>Rome</hi> have provoked the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Otto</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> in his Speech to the Biſhops, as it is received by <hi>Aventine,</hi> in his ſeventh Book of the Annals of <hi>Bris,</hi> pag. 550.</note> and by the Direction of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great <hi>Pope</hi> have defended mine by Armes. This Man being dead, you had Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop is Antichriſt: And I have fell from the forſaken Sect of the Chief Priest, to the Emperour, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41796:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Contra Purgatorium &amp; Limbum Infantium.</head>
               <p>AD refrigerium juſti vocantur,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprianus</hi> in libro de Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitate Sectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne undecima,</note> ad ſupplicium rapiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur injuſti; datur velocius tutela ſidentibus, Perſidis poena.</p>
               <p>Primum enim locum fides Catholicorum Divina Authoritate regnum credit eſſe Caelorum, unde, ut dixi,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> Septimo tomo, libro quinto <hi>Hipognoſticôt</hi> contra Pelagia nos, Pagina nongen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſima quinquagefimâ ſeptimâ.</note> non Baptizatus excipitur. Secundum gehennam; ubi omnis Apoſtata vel à Chriſti Fide alienus Eterna ſupplicia experietur. Tertium pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ignoramus, imo nec eſſe in Scripturis Sanctis invenie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Finge <hi>Pelagiane</hi> locum ex Officina dogmatis tui.</p>
               <p>Scitote verò, quòd cùm anima à corpore evellitur,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> tomo nono, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro de vanitat ſeculi, capite primo.</note> ſtatim aut in Paradiſo pro meretis bonis collocatur, aut certè pro pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis in inferni tartara praecipitatur. Eligite modò quod vultis, &amp; hoc jam in vita veſtra diſponite, aut Perpetualiter gaudere cum Sanctis, aut ſine fine cruciari cum impiis.</p>
               <p>Nemo ſe decipiat, fratres, duo enim loca ſunt,<note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo decimo de tempore ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne dacente ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſecundo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> etiam idem in effectu dicit tomo ſeptimo, libro primo de peccatorum meritis &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione, capite vigeſimo octavo. Et quinto tomo, libro vigeſimo primo de civitate Dei, capite vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſimo quinto.</p>
                  </note> &amp; tertius non eſt ullis, qui cum Chriſto regnare non meruerit, cum Diabolo abſque dubitatione ulla peribit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secundò. Contra invocatio Angelorum, &amp; Sanctorum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortuorum, &amp; facientem eos Mediatores &amp; Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores.</head>
               <p>QUòd non oporteat Eccleſiam Dei relinquere,<note place="margin">Conſilium <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicenum</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none trigeſin quinto.</note> &amp; abire at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Angelos nominare, &amp; congregationes facere, quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicta noſcuntur. Si quis igitur inventus fuerit huic oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultae Idololatriae ſerviens, ſit anathema, quia derelinquit Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num noſtrum Jeſum Chriſtum Filium Dei, &amp; ſe Idololatriae tradidit.</p>
               <p>Quoniam enim illi Angelos jubebant adorare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoretus</hi> in caput tert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ad <hi>Coloſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Clemens Papa &amp; Martyr li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro ſecundo conſtitutionum Apoſtolicarum capite trigeſimo Secundo. Origines contra celſum, libro. Octavo.</note> ipſe contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um praecipit, ut &amp; dicta &amp; facta exornent recordatione Chriſti Domini: &amp; Deo, inquit, &amp; Patri gratiarum actionem emittite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41796:7"/>per ipſum, non per Angelos. Hanc etiam legem ſequens <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cena</hi> Synodus, &amp; volens veteri illi morbo mederi, lege cavit ne precarentur Angelos, &amp; ne relinquerent Dominum noſtrum Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Chriſtum.</p>
               <p>Non enim ad Omnipotem Deum accedere licet, niſi per Chriſtum.</p>
               <p>Cùm autem dicit, nobis tamen unus Deus Pater ex quo omnia, vocem hanc, nobis, dicit de ſeipſo, &amp; omnibus qui adſcenderunt ad ſummum Deum Deorum, &amp; ad ſummum Dominum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum. Adſcendit autem ad ſummum Deum is, qui eum inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parabiliter &amp; indiviſibiliter colit, per Jeſum Dei Filium, cujus ſolius ductu pervenitur ad Patrem.</p>
               <p>Ad petendum cum fiducia impellens eos, amen amen affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans dixit, impetrabitis à Patre quicquid in nomine meo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieritis. In nomine autem meo, addidit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cytillus</hi> libro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> decimo in <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nneun,</hi> capite Septi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ut Mediatorem ſe &amp; Collargitorem oſtendat. Nullus enim accedit ad Patrem, niſi per Filium.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Athanaſius</hi> etiam contra <hi>Arianos</hi> oratione quartâ, Paginâ ducenteſimâ quinquageſimâ nonâ agens de verbis <hi>Pauli</hi> ad <hi>Theſſalonicenſes;</hi> &amp; <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> Octavo tomo, in enarratione Pſalmi centeſimi Octavi, ſimilia clarè dicunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertiò. Contra applicationem unius Operum ad alium.</head>
               <p>QUia prodire obviam fatuae (Virgines) extinctis lampadibus non poſſunt, deprecantur eas quae prudentes erant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hilarius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentario in <hi>Marthaeum</hi> canone vigeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſeptimo.</note> ut oleum mutuent. Quibus reſponderunt non poſſe ſe dare, quia non ſit fortè quod omnibus ſatis ſit, alienis ſcilicet operibus ac meritis neminem adjuvandum, quia unicuique lampadi ſuae emere oleum ſit neceſſe.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Leo</hi> Magnus Epiſtolâ Octogeſima primâ, quae eſt ad Paleſtinos Monachos. Primo tomo conciliorum, Paginâ Septingenteſimâ Nenageſimâ primâ: Et <hi>Leo</hi> Papa in Epiſtola Nonageſima quinta Scriptum ad <hi>Leonem Auguſtum,</hi> clarè etiam fimile dicunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41796:8"/>
               <head>Quartò. Contra Adorationem Angelorum, Martyrum, &amp; Sanctorum demortuorum.</head>
               <p>SIt in honore <hi>Maria:</hi> Pater &amp; Filius &amp; Spiritus Sanctus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretur. <hi>Mariam</hi> nemo Adoret, non dico Mulierem,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in libro tertio, hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſi Septuageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Nonâ.</note> imò neque virum: Deo debetur hoc Myſterium. Neque Angeli capiunt talem glorificationem. Deleantur quae malè ſcripta ſunt in corde deceptorum. Tollatur ex oculis cupiditas ligni. Convertatur rurſus figmentum ad Dominum; revertatur <hi>Eva</hi> cum <hi>Adam,</hi> ut Deum colat ſolum; ne ducatur ſerpentis, voce, ſed permaneat in Dei praecepto, ne comedas de ligno; &amp; erat lignum, non error, fed per ipſum lignum facta eſt inobedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia erroris: Ne comedat quis de errore, qui eſt propter ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam Mariam. Nam etſi pulchrum eſt lignum, ſed tamen non ad cibum. Etſi Pulcherrima eſt <hi>Maria,</hi> &amp; Sancta &amp; honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta; at non ad Adorationem. Hae verò rurſus renovant ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae mixturam &amp; praeparant Diabolo &amp; non Deo menſam, velut ſcriptum eſt, &amp; paſcuntur cibo impietatis, velut dicit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina ſcriptura, &amp; ſoeminae ferunt Pollinem, &amp; filii colligunt ligna, ut faciant placentas oleo ſubactas exercitui Coeli, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcantur à <hi>Jeremia</hi> tales Mulieres &amp; ne turbent orbem Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum: Ne dicant, honoramus Reginam Coeli. Novit enim <hi>Taphnas</hi> has Punire; noverunt loci horum aedificiorum corpora ſuſcipere ad Putrifactionem.</p>
               <p>At Sanctos Martyres neque Deos eſſe dicimus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyrillus Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> tertio Tomo, libro Sexto contra <hi>Julianum</hi> folio quinquageſimo, literâ A.</note> neque ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare conſuevimus: laudamus autem eos Potiùs ſummis hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, quod pro veritate ſtrenuè certarunt, &amp; fidei ſincerita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſervarunt, ita ut ſuam animam contempſerint, &amp; mortis terroribus valedicentes Praevaluerint in ſummis periculis, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taeque fuerint fortitudinis, quaſi ſtatuas ſibi ſuae vitae exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41796:9"/>
               <p>Nos autem non dico martyrum reliquias,<note place="margin">Hierenymus in Secundo tomo Epiſtolâ adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus vigilantium ad Riparium Presbyterum, Paginâ Cente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimâ decima nonâ.</note> ſed ne ſolem qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; Lunam, non Angelos, non Archangelos, non Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bim, non Seraphim, &amp; omne nomen quod nominatur, &amp; in praeſenti ſeculo &amp; in futuro, colimus &amp; adoramus: ne ſervia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus creaturae potiùs quàm Creatori, qui eſt benedictus in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula.</p>
               <p>Non ſit nobis religio cultus hominum mortuorum: quia ſi piè vixerint, non ſic habentur ut tales quaerant honores;<note place="margin">Auguſtinus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Primo, libro de vera religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, capite quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quageſimo quinto.</note> ſed illum à nobis coli volunt, quo illuminante laetantur meriti ſui nos eſſe conſervos. Honorandi ergo ſunt propter imitationem, non ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi propter religionem: Si autem malè vixerint, ubicunque ſint, non ſunt colendi.<note place="bottom">Auguſtinus etiam primo tomo, libro de moribus Eccleſiae Catholicae, capite trigeſimo; Cyrillus Alexandrinus libro ſecundo Theſauri, capite primo contra Eunomium; Ambroſius libro primo de fide ad Gratianum Auguſtum, capite ſeptimo; &amp; multi alii ſimilia dicunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quintò. Contra Adorationem imaginum.</head>
               <p>PLacuit, picturas in Eccleſia eſſe non debere,<note place="margin">Concilium Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berinum tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Conſtantini Magni celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, trigeſimo ſexto Canone, Tertullianus libro de corona militis capite decimo.</note> ne quod coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aut adoratur, in parietibus depingatur.</p>
               <p>Johannes filioli, inquit, cuſtodite vos ab idolis: non jam ab idolatria quaſi ab officio, ſed ab idolis, id eſt, ab ipſa effigie eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum indignum enim ut imago Dei vivi, imago idoli &amp; mortui fiat.</p>
               <p>Non eſt dubium, quin religio nulla ſit, ubicunque ſimulacrum eſt, nam ſi religio ex divinis rebus eſt, divini autem nihil eſt,<note place="margin">Lactantius di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinarum inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutionum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do libro, capite decimo nono.</note> niſi in caeleſtibus rebus: carent ergo religione ſimulacre: quia nihil poteſt eſſe caeleſte in ea re, quae fit ex terra: quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem de nomine ipſo ſapienti apparere poteſt. Quicquid enim ſimulatur, id falſum ſit, neceſſe eſt: nec poteſt unquam veri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men accipere, quod veritatem fuco, &amp; imitatione mentitur. Si autem omnis imitatio, non res potiſſimùm ſeria ſed quaſi ludus ac jocus eſt: non religio in ſimulacris, ſed minus reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41796:10"/>eſt. Praeferendum eſt igitur verum omnibus falſis, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda terrena ut Caeleſtia conſequamur.</p>
               <p>Attendite vobis, ut ſervetis traditionis quas accepiſtis.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphanius Cyprius</hi> ut ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur à Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio Neocaſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſi actione Sexta Synodi Nicenae Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae.</note> Ne declinetis neque ad dextera neque ad ſiniſtra, quibus infert haec: Eſtote memores dilecti filii, ne in Eccleſiam imagines infera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, neque in Sanctorum caemeteriis eas ſtatuatis, ſed perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuò circumferte Deum in cordibus veſtris. Quinetiam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in domo communi tollerentur, non enim fas eſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum per oculos ſuſpenſum teneri, ſed per occupationem mentis.</p>
               <p>Idolum tam fieri quam coli Deus prohibet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullianus</hi> libro de Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria, capite quarto.</note> quanto praecedit ut fiat quod coli poſſit, tanto prius eſt ne fiat ſi coli non licet. Propter hanc cauſam, ad eradicandam ſcilicet materiam Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latriae, lex divina proclamat: Ne feceritis idolum, &amp; conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens, neque ſimilitudinem eorum quae in coelo ſunt, &amp; quae in Terra, &amp; quae in Mari: Toto Mundo ejuſmodi artibus inter dixit ſervis Dei. Anteceſſerat enim hoc praedicens <hi>Enoch,</hi> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Elementa omnem mundi ſenſum, quae Coelo, quae Mari, quae Terrâ continentur, in Idolatriam verſuros daemonas, &amp; Spiritus deſertorum Angelorum, ut pro Deo adverſus Dominum conſecrarentur. Omnia igitur colit humanus error, Praeter ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum omnium conditorem eorum imagines Idola, imaginum conſecratio Idolatria. Quicquid Idololatra committit, in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificem quemcunque &amp; cujuſcunque Idoli deputetur neceſſe eſt. Denique idem <hi>Enoch</hi> ſimul &amp; cultores Idoli, &amp; fabricatores in comminatione praedamnat.</p>
               <p>Juro vobis peccatores,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> quod in diem ſanguinis perditionis pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia parata eſt. Qui ſervitis lapidibus, &amp; qui imagines faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aureas, &amp; argenteas, &amp; ligneas, &amp; lapideas, &amp; fictiles, &amp; ſervitis phantaſmatibus, &amp; Daemoniis, &amp; Spiritibus infamibus, &amp; omnibus erroribus non ſecundùm ſcientiam, nullum ab iis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venietis
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41796:11"/>auxilium. <hi>Eſaias</hi> verò, teſtes, ait, vos eſtis, ſi eſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us abſque me. Et non erant tunc qui fingunt &amp; exſculpunt, omnes vani qui faciunt libita ſibi, quae illis non Proderunt. Et deinceps tota illa pronunciatio, quà in artifices, quà in cultores deteſtatur, cujus clauſula eſt, cognoſcite quòd cinis ſit cor illorum, &amp; errant, &amp; nemo animam ſuam liberare poſſit. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi aequè <hi>David,</hi> &amp; tales fiant, inquit, qui faciunt ea. Et quid ego modicae memoriae homo ultrà quid ſuggeram, quid recolam de Scripturis, quaſi aut non ſufficiat vox Spiritus Sancti, aut ultrà deliberandum ſit, an maledixeratque damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit Dominus ipſos priùs artifices eorum, quorum cultores male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit &amp; damnat.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Juſtinus</hi> Martyr Dialogo cum <hi>Tryphone</hi> judaeo, paginâ ducenteſimâ quinquageſima primâ etiam; <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> oratione adhortatoria ad Gentes paginâ viceſima quintâ editionis Latina florentini; <hi>Tertullianus</hi> in Scorpiaco adverſus Gnoſticos capite Secundo; Et multi alii ſimilia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sextò. Contra Adorationem Sanctarum Reliquiarum.</head>
               <p>NOs non dico Martyrum reliquias,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronimus</hi> Epiſtolâ ad Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parium adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus vigilanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſecundo tomo, folio cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſimo decimo. nono &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente. <hi>Vigilantius</hi> Presbyter ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ab Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo dictus primo tomo Etiſtold ad Paulinum, folio centteſimo Sexto; quod &amp; <hi>Caeſar Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> fatetur An. Eccl. tom. <hi>5.</hi> in An. Dom <hi>406.</hi> ſic ſcribit. ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert <hi>Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> ipſe <hi>2</hi> do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, Epiſtolâ ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, folio cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſimo vigeſimo tertio.</note> ſed ne Solem quidem &amp; Lunam, non Angelos, non Archangelos, non Cherubim, non Seraphim, &amp; omne nomen quod nominatur &amp; in Praeſenti ſeculo &amp; in futuro, colimus &amp; adoramus, ne ſerviamus Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae potiùs quam Creatori qui eſt benedictus in ſecula.</p>
               <p>Quid neceſſe eſt, te tanto honore, non ſolùm honorare, ſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam adorare illud neſcio quid quod in modico vaſculo transfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo colis?<note n="*" place="margin">Incodem libro etiam,</note> Quid pulverem linteamine circumdatum, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando oſcularis?<note n="†" place="margin">&amp; Poſteà, dicit.</note> Propè ritum Gentilium videmus ſub praetex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu religionis introductum in Eccleſiis, ſole adhuc fulgente, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les cereorum accendi, &amp; ubicunque pulviſculum neſcio quod, in modico vaſculo precioſo linteamine circumdatum oſculantes adorant, magnum honorem praebent hujuſmodi homines bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimis Martyribus, quos putant de viliſſimis cereolis illuſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41796:12"/>quos Agnus, qui eſt in medio throni cum omni fulgore Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatis ſuae illuſtrat.<note place="bottom">Concilium <hi>Elib erinum</hi> etiam, tempore <hi>Conſtantini</hi> Magni celebratum, Canone trigeſimo quarto, &amp; Canone ſequente ait ſimilia.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Septimò. Contra Tranſubſtantiationem, &amp; conſe quentiâ, Hoſtiae Adorationem.</head>
               <p>DOminus cùm accepiſſet ſymbolum ſeu ſignum, non dixit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoretus</hi> ſecundo tomo, Dialoge primo.</note> hoc eſt Deitas mea, ſed hoc eſt corpus meum.</p>
               <p>Dedit enim ſui corporis imaginem vel Effigiem aut typum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulis,<note place="margin">Procopius Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaeus in gen quadrageſ. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num caput.</note> haud amplius admittens cruenta Legis Sacrificia.</p>
               <p>Acceptum Panem &amp; diſtributum diſcipulis;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertullianus</hi> libro quarto adverſus <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionem,</hi> capite decimo nono.</note> corpus ſuum illum fecit, hoc eſt corpus meum dicendo, id eſt, figura corporis mei. Figura autem non fuiſſet, niſi veritatis eſſet corpus. Caeterùm vacua res quod eſt phantaſma, figuram capere non Poſſet.</p>
               <p>Dicit ſacerdos: Fac nobis hanc oblationem adſcriptam, ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabilem,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſius</hi> de Sacramentis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre quarto, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite quinto.</note> acceptabilem, quod eſt figura corporis &amp; ſanguinis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti.</p>
               <p>Dominus Judam adhibuit ad Convivium,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> in Pſalmum ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> in quo corporis &amp; ſanguinis ſui figuram diſcipulis ſuis commendavit &amp; tradidit.</p>
               <p>Inſpice item diligenter, quomodo ſumens in manibus Panem,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephrem Syrus</hi> ad eos qui Filii Dei naturam ſcrutari volunt cap. quarto.</note> benedicit ac frangit in figuram immaculati corporis ſui, calicem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in figuram pretioſi ſui ſanguinis benedicit &amp; tribuit diſcipulis ſuis.<note place="bottom">Idem in finu etiam dicunt <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> in Epiſtola ad Alcuinum de ratione ſeptuageſimae, in libro de divinis officiis; <hi>Bertramus</hi> de cana Domini; Origines contra Marcionitas, dialogo tertio; <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> homilia octogeſima tertiâ in <hi>Matthaeum;</hi> multi alii <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41796:13"/>
               <head>Octavò. Contra Adorationem Altaris, Crucis, &amp; omnium Creaturarum an Dei Creationis, an hominis inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ſint.</head>
               <p>MErito Eccleſia Catholica Mater Chriſtianorum veriſſima,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus primo tomo, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro de moribus Eccleſia Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae, capite tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſimo.</note> non ſolùm ipſum Deum, cujus adeptio vita eſt beatiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, puriſſimè atque caſtiſſimè colendum praedicat, nullum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis adorandam Creaturam inducens, cui ſervire jubeamur: &amp; ab illa incorrupta &amp; inviolabili aeternitate, cui ſoli homo ſubji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendus eſt, cui ſoli rationalis anima cohaerendo non miſera eſt, excludens omne quod factum eſt, quod obnoxium commutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, quod ſubditum tempori.<note place="bottom">Idem etiam affirmat Epiphanius libro ſecundo contra Originem Adamantium, baereſi Sexageſima quarta, Paginâ ducenteſimâ trigeſima primâ.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nonò. Contra Precem prr mortuis.</head>
               <p>LEgite Salvatoris Scripturas, &amp; diſcite,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtomus homiliâ vigeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſecundâ ad Populum Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochenum.</note> quomodo nos hinc illuc migrantes adjuvare poteſt nemo non frater fratrem redimet, ex interminabilibus tormentis: non amicus amicum, non parentes filios, non filii parentes. Et quid dico homines miſerabiles, cùm neque ſi <hi>Noe</hi> veniat, &amp; <hi>Job,</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniel,</hi> tunc judicantem exorare poſſinr.</p>
               <p>Dum in praeſenti ſeculo ſumus, ſive orationibus,<note place="margin">Hieronymus Commentariis ad capurſex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um Epiſtolae ad Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latas ad ea ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, unuſquiſque onus ſuum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit.</note> ſive conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis invicem poſſe nos coadjuvari. Cùm autem antè tribunal Chriſti venerimus, non <hi>Job,</hi> non <hi>Daniel,</hi> nec <hi>Noe</hi> rogare poſſe pro quoquam: ſed unumquemque portare onus ſnum.<note place="bottom">Idem etiam in ſenſu ait Auguſtinus decimo tomo, Sermone trigeſimo ſecundo de verbis Apoſtoli.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41796:14"/>
               <head>Decimò. Contra Meritum Humanum.</head>
               <p>PEccatorum remiſſio non probitatis eſt meritum,<note place="margin">Hilarens in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerratione Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi ſexageſimi Sexti ſubiniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> ſed Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneae indulgentiae, voluntas ex bonitatis divitiis ad miſeran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di munus exuberans.</p>
               <p>Etſi ad opus virtutis excrevero, ad vitam non ex meritis,<note place="margin">Gregorius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus Epiſcopus Romanus libro nono Expoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Moralis in Jobum-capite undecimo.</note> ſed ex venia convaleſco.</p>
               <p>Ubi ergo, ait, ſunt merita noſtra, aut ubi eſt ſpes noſtra? au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di inquam, non ex operibus juſtitiae quae fecimus nos, ſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundùm ſuam miſericordiam ſalvos nos fecit. Quid enim? tu fortè putaveras tua te creaſſe merita,<note place="margin">Bernardus tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatu de Gratia &amp; libro arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio ab initio fermè.</note> tuâ poſſe ſalvari juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, qui nec ſaltem Dominum Jeſum dicere potes niſi in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu Sancto? itane oblitus es qui dixerit: Sine me nihil pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis facere? Et neque currentis, neque volentis, ſed Dei miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis eſt.<note place="bottom">Idem etiam in effectu dicit Hilarius in Enerratione Pſalmi quinquageſimi primi, non procul à fine.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Undecimò. Contra Confeſſionem Auricularem.</head>
               <p>NOn te in conſervorum tuorum theatrum duco,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtomus homiliâ ſecundâ in Pſalmum quinquageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</note> non homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus peccata tua detegere cogo repete coram Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam tuam &amp; explica. Oſtende Domino praeſtantiſſimo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico, tua vulnera &amp; pete ab eo Medicamentum: Oſtende ei qui nihil opprobret, ſed humaniſſimè curet.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41796:15"/>
               <p>Quid mihi ergo eſt cum hominibus ut audeant confeſſiones meas, quaſi ipſi ſanaturi ſint omnes languores meos?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſtious</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo primo, libro decimo confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionum, capite tertio.</note> curioſum genus ad cognoſcendam vitam alienam, deſidioſum ad corrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſuam. Quid à me quaerunt audire qui ſim, qui nolunt te (Deus mi) audire qui ſint? Et unde ſciunt cùm à meipſo de me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo audiunt, an verum dicam, quandoquidem nemo ſcit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum quid agatur in homine, niſi Spiritus hominis qui in ipſo eſt.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> etiam in effectu idem dicit homiliâ trigeſimâ primâ in Epiſtolam ad hebraeus in caput duodecimum, Paginâ Milleſimâ Nongenteſimâ Quinquageſimâ Sextâ, editionis comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linianae.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Duodecimò. Contra ſatisfactionem Humanam.</head>
               <p>PEtrus doluit &amp; flevit, quia erravit ut homo.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſius</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Lucam ad caput vigeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſe cundum. <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no tomo, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatu ſecundo in primam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolam Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis.</note> Non invenio quid dixerit invenio quod fleverit. Lacrymas ejus lego, ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem non lego.</p>
               <p>Dimittuntur vobis Peccata per nomen ejus, non per hominis alicujus.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Cyprianus</hi> in effectu etiam dicit idem ſermone de ablutione nedum ſectione ultima.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimo Tertiò. Contra Peregrinationes.</head>
               <p>NOn Hieroſolimis fuiſſe, ſed Hieroſolimis is bene vixiſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronimus</hi> in Epiſtola ad <hi>Panlinum</hi> de inſtitutione Monachi primo tomo, folio cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſimo tertio.</note> lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandum eſt, illa expetenda eſt civitas, non quae occîdit Prophetas, &amp; Chriſti Sanguinem fudit, ſed quam fluminis impetus laetificat; quae in monte ſita caelari non poteſt, quam matrem Sanctorum Apoſtolus clamitat; in qua ſe municipatum cum juſtis
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41796:16"/>habere laetatur. Neque verò hoc dicens, memet ipſum incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae redarguo, damnóque quod facio; ut fruſtrà videar ad exemplum <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; meos &amp; Patriam reliquiſſe: Sed non audeo Dei Omnipotentiam auguſto fine concludere, &amp; coar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare parvo terrae loco, quem non capit Coelum. Singuli qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que credentium, non locorum diverſitatibus, ſed fidei merito, ponderantur. Et veri Adoratores, neque Hieroſolymis neque in Monte <hi>Gazarim</hi> Adorant Patrem; quia Deus Spiritus eſt, &amp; Adoratores ejus in Spiritu &amp; veritate Adorare oportet. Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſpirat ubi vult Domini eſt Terra &amp; plenitudo ejus. Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm ſiccato judeae vellere, Univerſus Orbis Caeleſti rore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſus eſt, &amp; multi de Oriente &amp; occidente venientes, recubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt in ſinu <hi>Abrahae;</hi> deſiit notus eſſe tantùm in <hi>Judaea</hi> Deus, &amp; in <hi>Iſrael</hi> magnum nomen ejus, ſed in omnem Terram exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit ſonus Apoſtolorum, &amp; in Finis Orbis Terrae verba eorum. Salvator ad Diſcipulos loquens cùm eſſet in Templo: Surgite, inquit, abeamus hinc, &amp; ad Judaeos: Relinquetur vobis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus veſtra deſerta. Si Coelum &amp; Terra tranſibunt, utique tranſibunt omnia quae terrena ſunt. Et crucis igitur &amp; Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionis loca proſunt his, qui portant crucem ſuam; &amp; cum Chriſto reſurgunt quotidie, qui dignos ſe exhibent tanto habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taculo. Caeterùm qui dicunt Templum Domini, Templum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, audiant ab Apoſtolo; vos eſtis Templum Domini, &amp; Spiritus Sanctus habitat in vobis. Et de Hieroſolymis &amp; de Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannia aequaliter patet aula Caeleſtis: Regnum enim Dei intra vos eſt <hi>Antonius,</hi> &amp; cuncta <hi>Aegypti</hi> &amp; <hi>Meſopotamiae, Ponti, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padociae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Armeniae</hi> examina Monachorum, non videre <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolymam;</hi> &amp; patet illis abſque hac Urbe <hi>Paradiſi</hi> janua. Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>Hilarion,</hi> cùm <hi>Palaeſtinus</hi> eſſet, &amp; in <hi>Palaeſtina</hi> viveret, uno tantùm die vidit <hi>Hieroſolymam,</hi> ut nec contemnere loca San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta propter viciniam, nec rurſus Dominum loco claudere vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur.</p>
               <p>Quorſum, inquies, haec tam longo repetita Principio?<note place="margin">Ibidem Paulò Pòſt.</note> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delicet ne quicquam fidei tuae deeſſe putes, quia Hieroſoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam non vidiſti; nec nos idcirco meliores exiſtimes, quod hujus loci habitaculo fruimur: Sed ſive hic ſive alibi, aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41796:17"/>te pro operibus tuis apud Dominum noſtrum habere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem.<note place="bottom">Claudius Taurinenſis Eccleſiae Epiſcopus adverſus Theodemirum Abbatem de Peregrinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne religionis causâ in urbem Romam, in quinto tomo Orthodoxographorum Jona Aurelianenſi Epiſcopo referente libro tertio de cultu imaginum, paginâ milleſimâ quingenteſimâ, ſeptuageſimâ, ſimile etiam clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimo Quartò. Contra Sacrificium.</head>
               <p>NEc dixit, qui tollet aut tulit: ſed tollit peccata mundi,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtemus in caput primum Johannis, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâ decima ſe p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timâ de verbis Johannis Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtae, ecce Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ille Dei qui tollit peccata mundi.</note> ut quotidie ea tollere intelligatur. Non enim cùm paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt; ſolùm noſtra abſtulit peccata, ſed ex illo hactenus tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Non ſemper Crucifigitur; unum namque pro peccatis noſtris tulit Sacrificium, ſed ſemper per illud nos purgat.</p>
               <p>Morte ſua quippe uno veriſſimo Sacrificio pro nobis oblato, quicquid culparum erat unde nos principatus &amp; poteſtates ad luenda ſupplicia jure detinebant, purgavit, abolevit, extinxit,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus tertio tomo, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro quarto de trinitate, capite decimo tertio.</note> &amp; ſua reſurrectione in novam vitam nos praedeſtinatos vocavit, vocatos juſtificavit, juſtificatos glorificavit.<note place="bottom">Auguſtinus etiam in Encbiridio ad Laurentium, capite Sexageſimo ſecundo clarè ſimile dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimo Quintò. Quod nec Petrus fuerit Apoſtolorum, nec Papa Eccleſiae, Caput.</head>
               <p>HOc erant utique &amp; caeteri Apoſtoli, quod fuit Petrus,<note place="margin">Cyprianus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. libro de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Eccleſia ſectione tertia.</note> Pari conſortio praediti &amp; honoris &amp; poteſtatis.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41796:18"/>
               <p>Chriſtus Apoſtolis omnibus poſt Reſurrectionem ſuam parem poteſtatem tribuit.<note place="margin">Ibidem Paulò antè.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Quicunque deſideraverit Primatum in Terra,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> homilâ quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſima tertiâ operis imperſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti in <hi>Matthae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> ad cap. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſ. tertium. <hi>Hieronymus</hi> in Epiſtola ad Evagrium.</note> inveniet confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem in Coelo, nec inter ſervos Chriſti computabitur, qui de Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matu tractaverit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ubicunque fuerit, Epiſcopus, ſive Romae, ſive Eugubii, ſive Conſtantinopoli, ſive Rhegii, ſive <hi>Alexandriae,</hi> ſive Tanis, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem meriti, ejuſdem eſt &amp; ſacerdotii. Potentia divitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; paupertatis humilitas, vel ſublimiorem vel inferiorem Epiſcopum non fuit. Caeterùm omnes Apoſtolorum ſucceſſores ſunt.</p>
               <p>Nullus Patriarcharum Univerſalis vocabulo unquam utatur.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pelagius 2.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Epiſt. om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Epiſcopis illicitè à Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanne Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopolitano convocatis. <hi>Gregorius</hi> Magnus Epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum ex regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro libro quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Epiſtolâ tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſimâ ſecunda quae eſt ad Mauricium Auguſtum.</note>Quia ſi unus Patriarcha Univerſalis dicitur, Patriarcharum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men caeteris derogatur. Sed abſit, hoc, abſit à fidelis cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam mente, hoc ſibi vel velle quempiam arripere, unde hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fratrum ſuorum imminueri ex quantulacunque parte vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur. Quapropter charitas veſtra neminem unquam ſuis in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolis Univerſalem nominet, ne ſibi debitum ſubtrahat, cùm al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri honorem defert indebitum.</p>
               <p>Abſit à cordibus Chriſtianorum nomen iſtud Blaſphemiae, in quo omnium ſacerdotum honor adimitur, dum ab uno ſibi demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter arrogatur.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> in caput Primum Actorum Apoſtolicorum, Et Gregorius Magnus quarto libro E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolarum ex regiſtro Epiſtolâ trigeſima quartâ quae eſt ad conſtantiam Auguſtam ſimilia etiam clarè dicunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:41796:19"/>
               <head>Decimo Sextò. Contra infallibilitatem Eccleſiae Romanae.</head>
               <p>POſt tanta beneficia verterunt in contemptum Privilegia dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronymus</hi> in caput Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <hi>Jeremiae,</hi> ſic invehitur in Sacerdotes <hi>Romanos. Hieronymus</hi> de ſeptem ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Eccleſiae, capite quinto, quemadmodum citatur in jure Canonico, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctione nona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſima tertiâ capitolo Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, quod in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine eſt vigeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tertium. <hi>Euſebius</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticae hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriae quinto libro, capite vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſimo.</note> ut Sacerdotes Dominum non quaererent, ut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores Legis ignorarent eum, qui alios docere debebant, &amp; Paſtores per negligentiam praevaricatores fierent, &amp; Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae qui in Populis diſputant, non Deo loquantur, ſed Idolo, &amp; ſua figmenta venerentur, his autem verbis utendum eſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus noſtri ordinis Magiſtros, qui devorant plebem Dei, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nunc autem ex quo in Eccleſiis, ſicut in Romano imperio, crevit avaritia; periit Lex de Sacèrdote &amp; viſio de Propheta. Singuli quippe per potentiam Epiſcopalis nominis, quam ſibi ipſe illicitè abſque Eccleſia vindicarunt, totum quod Levitarum eſt, in uſus ſuos redigunt; nec hoc ſibi quod ſcriptum eſt, vindicant, ſed cunctis auferunt Univerſa, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Per idem tempus in Urbe <hi>Roma,</hi> diverſis novitatibus per non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullus regula traditionis Eccleſiaſtica vexabatur.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Hieronymus</hi> ad Evagrium Epiſcopum, Epiſtolâ octogeſima quintâ, tomo ſecundo, ut citatur in jure Canonieo eadem diſtinctione ſupradicta, capitolo quod eſt in ordine vigeſimum quartum ſimile eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimo Septimò. Contra diſpenſationes Papales.</head>
               <p>STare non valet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gratianus</hi> in Rubricam, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulò octavò.</note> quod contra Evangelicam vel Propheticam Doctrinam ſeu conſtitutionem factum fuerit.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41796:20"/>
               <p>Nec quicquam,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marcellinus</hi> Papa Epiſtolâ Secundâ.</note> quod contra Evangelicae vel Propheticae aut Apoſtolicae doctrinae conſtitutionem, ſucceſſorumve eorum, ſive Sanctorum Patrum actum fuerit, ſtabit.</p>
               <p>Non eſt in Poteſtate Papae aut concilii aut Eccleſiae,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gerſon</hi> de vita ſpirituali ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</note> immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare traditiones datas ab Evangeliſtis &amp; à Paulo, ſicut quidam delirant.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Urbanus</hi> Papa etiam, ut citatur in jure canonico, causâ vigeſima quintâ ſimile clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimo Octavò. Contra Ceremoniarum Multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</head>
               <p>HOc apud nos Superſtitioſae mulierculae, in parvulis Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronymus</hi> commentariis in caput vigeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tertium <hi>Matthaei. Petrus de Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aco</hi> Gardinalis Cameracenſis de Reformat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia de refor. Praelat.</note> &amp; in crucis ligno, &amp; iſtiuſmodi rebus; quae habent quidem zelum Dei, ſed non juxta ſcientiam, uſque hodie facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; culicem liquantes &amp; camelum glutientes.</p>
               <p>Providentem eſſet, quod in Divina Servitio, non tam onero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa prolixitas, quàm devota &amp; integra brevitas ſevaretur.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Johannes Gerſon</hi> etiam parte tertia operum, de vita ſpirituali animae, lectione ſecunda, ſimile clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41796:21"/>
               <head>Decimo Nonò. Contra Obligationem, aut in Sacerdoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, aut aliis, ad Caelibatum.</head>
               <p>REctè autem <hi>(Paulus)</hi> poſuit illud;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoretus</hi> in quartum cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put Primae E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeum.</hi>
                  </note> prohibentium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahere Matrimonium. Neque enim Caelibatum ac continentiam vituperat, ſed eos accuſat qui lege lata ea ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui compellunt.</p>
               <p>Integritas corporis expetenda à vobis eſt:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſius</hi> in libro exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ad virgines, ut citatur in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Canonico, causâ trigeſima ſecundiâ, quaeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ione ſecundâ, capitulo Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritas, quod nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero eſt deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tertium. Canon quintus Apoſtolorum. <hi>Hieronymus</hi> tomo primo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolarum, libro primo adverſus Jovinianum, pag. trigeſ ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, teſtatur.</note> quam ego pro conſilio ſuadeo, non pro imperio Praecipio. Sola eſt enim vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitas, quae ſuaderi poteſt, imperari non poteſt; res magis voti, quàm praecepti.</p>
               <p>Epiſcopus aut Presbyter aut Diaconus Uxorem propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am nequaquam ſub obtentu Religionis abjiciat. Si verò rejecerit Excommunicetur; ſed ſi perſeveraverit, dejicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
               <p>Suo tempore plurimos Sacerdotes habuiſſe Matrimonia, &amp; Apoſtolum Epiſcopum deſcribere unius uxoris virum, haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem filios cum omni caſtitate.</p>
               <p>Nec ratione, nec autoritate probatur,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cajetanus</hi> Cardinalis in Opuſc. <hi>Tit. 1.</hi> Tract. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> quod abſolutè lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendo, Sacerdos peccet, contrahendo Matrimonium; nec ordo, in quantum ordo; nec ordo in quantum ſacer, eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditivus Matrimonii.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41796:22"/>
               <p>Sacerdotium non dirimere contractum Matrimonii ſive ante, ſive poſt ordinationem, ſecluſis omnibus legibus,<note place="margin">Ibideus Paulò Poſt concludit.</note> ſtando tantùm in his quae à Chriſto &amp; ab Apoſtolis habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.<note place="bottom">Clemens Romanus Petri Apoſtoli Diſcipulus, &amp; ut Papiſtae volunt, in Epiſcopatu Romano Sueceſſor libro ſecundo Apoſtolicarum coeſtitutionum, capite ſecundo, deſcribens qualem opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teat eſſe Epiſcopum, ſimile etiam clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Viceſimò. Quòd ſola Norma, &amp; Fidei, &amp; Actionum, Sacrae Scripturae ſint.</head>
               <p>DEus nobis Legem dedit &amp; Teſtimonia Scripturarum;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronymus</hi> in <hi>Iſalae</hi> caput octavum in v. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> quae ſi ſequi nolueritis, non habebitis lucem, ſed ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per caligo vos opprimet.</p>
               <p>Sicut ſtellas Coeli non extinguit nox;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zepherinus</hi> Papa. Epiſt. Primâ ad Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos Siciliae, ut citatur in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Canonico, Diſtinct trigeſ. octavâ, capitulo ſicut quod in ordine octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum eſt.</note> ſic mentes fidelium firmamento inhaerentes Sacrae Scripturae, non obſcurat mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dana iniquitas.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41796:23"/>
               <p>Gentilis dicit, vellem fieri Chriſtianus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> in acta Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, homiliâ trigeſima tertiâ.</note> ſed neſcio cui adhaeream, multae ſunt inter vos Pugnae, neſcio quod dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eligam. Singuli dicunt: Ego verum dico, cui credam neſcio, cùm utrinque Scripturas praetexant. Reſpondeo illi; hoc multùm pro nobis. Nam ſi diceremus nos ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus credere, meritò turbareris: Sed cùm Scripturas accipimus &amp; illae ſunt ſimplices &amp; verae, facilè tibi fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit judicare. Si quis illis conſentit, Chriſtianus eſt; Si quis contra illas, Procul eſt ab hoc Canone.</p>
               <p>Non relictus eſt hominum eloquiis de Dei rebus alius praeterquam Dei ſermo.<note place="margin">Hilarius de Trinitate libro Septimo, pag. centeſ. vigeſ. quintâ.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Oportet omne verbum aut rem confirmare teſtimonio Sacrae Scripturae,<note place="margin">Baſilius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Summae moralium <hi>26.</hi> cap. prime.</note> ad certitudinem quidem &amp; perfectionem bonorum, ad confuſionem verò malorum.</p>
               <p>Scriptura divinitùs inſpirata arbiter conſtituatur à no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; apud quos inventa fuerint dogmata Divinis Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus concordantia,<note place="margin">Baſilius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in libro E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolarum, octugeſima E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolâ, quae eſt ad Euſtathium medicum, pagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ ſeptingente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimâ decima quartâ, edit. Latinae Frobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianae, an. <hi>1560</hi>
                  </note> his omnino etiam veritatis Suffragium accedet.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Auguſtinus</hi> ſeptimo tomo, libro de unitate Eccleſiae, capite decimo ſexto, ſimile etiam clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41796:24"/>
               <head>Viceſſimo Primò. Quòd Seripturae contineant quicquid Doctrinae ad Salutem neceſſarium eſſe.</head>
               <p>OMnia Evangelium continet &amp; praeſentia &amp; futura,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtomus</hi> in Epiſtolam ad Titum, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liâ Prima.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem &amp; Pietatem, fidem, ſimul omnia praedicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis verbo concluſit.</p>
               <p>Non Omnia quae Deus fecit, conſcripta ſunt;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyrillus Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſed quae ſcribentes tam ad mores quam ad dogmata putarunt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ut recta ſide &amp; operibus rutilantes ad regnum C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum perveniamus per Jeſum Chriſtum.</p>
               <p>Omnis enim Scriptura, id eſt,<note place="margin">Cardinalis Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go de ſancto Charo in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilla ad <hi>2. T. 3.</hi>
                  </note> ſacra ſcriptura quae eſt de omnibus neceſſariis ad ſalutem, &amp; quae eſt omnis, id eſt, perfecta, &amp; ideo privilegiat ſibi nomen Scripturae per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonomaſiam.</p>
               <p>Sermo eſt de Sacris literis veteris Teſtamenti,<note place="margin">Cardinalis Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetanus in <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> quae te poſſunt inſtruere, pro, ſapientiam docere ad Salutem
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41796:25"/>per fidem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Habent enim facultatem docendi ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, non hujus mundi, ſed ad aeternam ſalutem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Item, perfectus, pro integer, conſtans ex omnibus requiſitis ad perficiendum hominem Dei.</p>
               <p>Quum multa feciſſet Dominus Jeſus,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no tomo, tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu quadrageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo nono in Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banuem.</note> non omnia Scripta ſunt: Electa autem ſunt quae ſcriberentur, quae ſaluti cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentium ſufficere videbantur.<note place="bottom">Tertullianus adverſus Hermogenem capite vigeſimo ſecundo, &amp; libro de carne Chriſti, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite ſeptimo, ſimile etiam clarè dicit.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Viceſimo Secundò. Quòd Solus Adorandus &amp; Invocandus eſt Deus.</head>
               <p>SOlus Adorandus eſt Deus optimus maximus,<note place="margin">Origines contra Celſum libro octavo.</note> Soli Preces offerendae unigenito Dei verbo.</p>
               <p>Soli Deo per Jeſum Preces offerre.<note place="margin">Ibidem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantò poſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Solum enim Creatorem illum omnium Deum adorare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicimus.<note place="margin">Euſebius de praeparatione Evangelica, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro quarto, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite quinto.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Neque adorandum quicquam praeter Deum legimus:<note place="margin">Ambroſius li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro tertio de Spiritu Sancta capite duodce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo.</note> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum eſt enim, Dominum Deum tuum adorabis, &amp; illi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſervies.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41796:26"/>
               <p>Sed tamen tu ſolus Domine invocandus es, tu rogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſius</hi> in Oratione de obitu Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſii follo centeſ. trigeſ. ſeptimo, litera <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note> ut eum (Theodoſium Magnum Imperatorem) in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis repreſentes.</p>
               <p>Is profectò veritatem conſervat, qui contrà non Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam,<note place="margin">Cyrillus Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrium libro duodecimo The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauei, capite primo.</note> ſed Creatorem colit, &amp; ei Soli ſervit.<note place="bottom">Dionyſius Alexandrinus ut refert Euſebius libro Septimo hiſtoriae Eccleſiaſticae, capite deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo: Et Auguſtinus prime tomo, libro de vora religione, capite quinquageſime quinto, ſimile etiam clarè dicunt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Viceſimo tertiò. Quod Papa ſit Antichriſtus.</head>
               <p>QUid eſt hoc Reverendiſſimi Patres,<note place="margin">Arnulphus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianenſis in concilio Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſi habito ſub Rege Capito, in quo depoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Arnulphus Rhemenſis Archiepiſcepus, ſic loquitur de Epiſcopo Romano. Huic Orationi etiam non contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixit Synodus, ſed ex ſententia Arnulphi. Aurelianenſis tum judicatum eſt, ut recitatur in Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turia decima Hiſtoriae Magdeburgicae Baſileae excuſae.</note> quid hunc in ſublimi ſolio reſidentem, veſtu purpurea &amp; auro radiantem, quid hunc, inquam, eſſe creditis? Nimirum ſi charitate Dei deſtituitur, ſolâque ſcientiâ inflatur &amp; extollitur, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtus eſt, in Templo Dei ſedens, &amp; ſe oftendens tanquam ſit Deus.</p>
               <p>Ego coactus ad <hi>Rom.</hi> Epiſcopum Provocari,<note place="margin">Otto Dux Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variae in Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, ut recitatur ab Aventinus libro ſeptimo Annalium Bojorum, Paginâ quingenteſimâ quin quageſimâ.</note> juſſuque Gregorij Pontificis Maximi Armis mea tutatus ſum. Hoc mortuo, <hi>Romanum</hi> Epiſcopum Antichriſtum eſſe praedicaſtis: Egoquè deſertâ Primarij Sacerdotis Sectâ, ad Imperatorem defeci, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:41796:27"/>
               <p>HE abuſeth the <hi>Caeſarion</hi> Sword (committed to us by the Will of Heaven) to the Temporal cares of this World,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lodewick</hi> the fourth Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in a Decree of a Councel of the Biſhops and Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſent held at <hi>Rome,</hi> and publiſhed at <hi>Rome</hi> the fourth Calend of <hi>May,</hi> in the year of Chriſt, 1328. Teſtifyeth thus of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> uſing it againſt the Divine precept; he gapeth after a Worldly Kingdom, as he is a counterfeit Paſtor, ſo he is a hidden Antichriſt, he is a Dog covered with a fine Skin, he ſtriveth with a wolfiſh Cruelty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtock of Chriſt, he ſelleth abominations, maketh againe of Hell, Heaven, and Celeſtial benefits, and hath Entered into a Covenant and Society with the Malicious <hi>Saracins,</hi> the <hi>Armenian</hi> Chriſtians five years together imploring his help.<note place="bottom">
                     <hi>Aventine</hi> alſo in his ſeventh Book of the Annals of <hi>Bois,</hi> reciteth very many, ſaying the like.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ENſe Caeſareo nobis à Caeli numine commiſſo,<note place="margin">Ludovicus quartus Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator in Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus conſulto, Epiſcoporum &amp; Principum Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia atque Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania conſenſu facto Romae, &amp; publicato Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae ad quartum Calendas Maii, Anno Chriſti, <hi>1328.</hi> de Papa Romano ſic teſtatur.</note> abutitur temporalibus hujus Seculi curis contra Divinum praecep tum incubat, regno mundano inhiat, ſicuti Paſtor eſt perſo natus, ita myſticus eſt Antichriſtus, canis pellicula tectus in gregem Chriſti lupina rabie graſſatur: Vendit ſcelera; In feros, ſuperos, beneficia caeleſtia cauponatur, cum Sarace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Armenios Chriſtianos quinque annis continentur ejus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem implorantes, infeſtantibus, faedus ſocietatemquè iniit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41796:27"/>
               <p>Theſe and the like Sayings of the Fathers, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to underſtand, and to that end, asking thoſe, under whom I was inſtructed, to unfold to me their meaning, they ſo abruptly and ſophiſtically expounded, that I became thereby (though I durſt not ſhew it) very much diſſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and had never that Opinion of the Fathers afterward, or at leaſt wiſe of theſe men, as I had before; and had I not given more credit to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, then to either of them, I had immediately fell from my then Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>When I had almoſt ended my Studies, the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> ſet upon me afreſh, thinking now to have prevailed with me to enter into their Order, but I anſwered them much what in the ſame manner I did before, and having a great deſire and full reſolution to Travel, (not ſo much out of any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, which was the only thing I pretended, as out of Curioſity) I withal told them (but it was only a pretence) that if I ever did enter into their Order, it could not be as yet; for I had made a vow to our Lady the Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to go to the Holy Land, to viſit the holy Sepulcher of her Dear Son our Saviour.</p>
               <p>I had no ſooner ended my Studies in Divinity, but (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving three hundred Pounds, left me ſome years before by an Uncle deceaſed, and diſpoſing of my moneys for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Bills of Exchange, ordering it to be paid me in other Countries upon ſight, according to my ſuppoſed Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) taking my Leave at the College, I betook my ſelf to my Journey, in which, going by <hi>Rome,</hi> and making my Addreſs to Cardinal <hi>Barbarini,</hi> he procured me the Popes Letters for my <hi>ſalva Conducta.</hi> And ſo departing thence I went for <hi>Naples,</hi> from thence to <hi>Manfredonia,</hi> from thence to <hi>Raguſa,</hi> from thence to <hi>Corfue,</hi> from thence to <hi>Zant,</hi> from thence to <hi>Candie,</hi> from thence to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> from thence to <hi>Cairo,</hi> from thence to <hi>Joppa;</hi> from thence to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41796:28"/>
                  <hi>Ramma,</hi> from thence to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from thence to <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> from thence to <hi>Nazereth,</hi> where ſeeing a Houſe, which they ſaid was the houſe of our Lady, I asked how many houſes our Lady had in the world, they ſaid, ſhe never had but one in the whole Univerſe, and that was it, I told them that in <hi>Europe</hi> we were credibly informed that her Houſe was in <hi>Italy,</hi> at a City called <hi>Lauretta,</hi> to whom People came out of all Parts on Pilgrimage, having been formerly brought from <hi>Nazereth</hi> thither by Angels: And asked them whether or no they had loſt any Houſe at any time, or had ever found one miſſing among them; They anſwered that then we were credibly informed a falſe thing; that the Houſe of <hi>Lauretta</hi> was a meer cheat; and that they had never loſt or miſſed any. This made me to think, that the <hi>Pope</hi> was either notoriouſly falſe, or meer fallible; notoriouſſy falſe, in cauſing us to adore a meer Fiction for our Ladies Houſe; or meer fallible, in taking that to be our Ladies Houſe which indeed was not.</p>
               <p>From thence returning by <hi>Ramma</hi> and <hi>Joppa,</hi> I came to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> from thence to <hi>Rhodes,</hi> from thence to <hi>Smirna,</hi> from thence to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſo to <hi>Caffa,</hi> from thence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning back to <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and ſeriouſly conſidering of what I had heard and ſeen in my Travels, I greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired the Grand Diverſity, I had obſerved in Religion. And being there with much diſſatisfyed, I now began to look for the aforeſaid Marks of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: but I ſoon perceived it to be in vain, for I either found ſhe had none at all, or none ſhe could claim as Peculiar to her ſelf. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> I ſaw ſhe was not, underſtanding the word to be <hi>Univerſal,</hi> which ſhe would always have us to do, for I ſaw others were more <hi>Univerſal</hi> then her ſelf, and there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be many <hi>Univerſal</hi> Churches. Beſides if ſhe were <hi>Univerſal,</hi> how could there be ſo much Diſpute, as daily there is, betwixt her and other Churches: for ſhe being
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41796:28"/>
                  <hi>Univerſal,</hi> there would be no other for her to diſpute with.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for Antiquity, I found it was no more in her than in other Churches; and in thoſe points wherein ſhe differed from the <hi>Greeks</hi> and others, ſhe had none at all: for Antiquity ought to be from the beginning; whereas the points in which ſhe differed from the <hi>Greeks</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches, were never thought of in the primitive times, nor long afterward.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for the Lineal Succeſſion of the Chair, I found that was no mark at all of the true Church; for the ſame was as well in other Churches, as that of <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides, the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſeeketh to draw its Succeſſion from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> was condemned by the reſt of the Chairs, who not only had their Succeſſion from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but from the other Apoſtles. And moreover St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith in his firſt Book and ſixth Chapter of Penitence, <hi>Non habent Hereditatem Petri, qui fidem</hi> Petri <hi>non habent,</hi> that thoſe have not the Succeſſion of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which have not St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If perpetual Continuance were a mark of the true Church, then I conſidered, we muſt ſtay until the end of the World, before we could know which was the true Church; for who knoweth until that time come, what Church may continue until that time come. A Church may exceedingly flouriſh now, which long before then may be utterly overthrown. Perpetual Continuance I concluded therefore was no good mark of a true Church; for beſides this, if Perpetual Continuance was a good mark, then divers Churches planted by the Apoſtles, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have long ſince ceaſed, were falſe Churches: and divers Churches which have continued ever ſince the Apoſtles time, and yet continue, though the Church of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41796:29"/>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> call them <hi>Heretical</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> would be true Churches. So that this Mark, though ſhe were ſure of it, as ſhe is not, would not only be no good Mark, but make againſt her ſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly. As for <hi>Unity,</hi> the fifth pretended Mark of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I found ſhe had it not by her own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; for if ſhe be Univerſal, as ſhe pretends ſhe is, then <hi>Proteſtants, Greeks, Arminians, Muſcovites, Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> and all other Chriſtians in the whole World, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Turks, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> are all of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church; and is there Unity amongſt theſe? If there be, what makes ſo much quarrelling and contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and them? But knowing ſhe was not Univerſal, I next conſidered her as ſhe was in her ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> a Particular Church. And taking her thus, never did I find in all my Travels, a Church more divided within it ſelf, both in Faith and Manners, than this of <hi>Rome.</hi> For as for their Faith, I obſerved it was not the ſame formerly as it is now, nor now as formerly: For for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they, believed the Sacrament of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> was to be received by the Laity in both kinds; now only in one. Formerly they believed a Prieſt might Marry, and ought not to be Shaven; now the quite contrary. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they believed Baptiſm was ſufficiently performed only with Water; now not without Water, Salt, Oyl, and Spittle. Formerly they believed the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> was to be given to Infants; now no ſuch thing. Thus in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Age they have either changed, added to, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from their Faith and Opinion; whereas a Church at Unity in it ſelf, always believes one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>And 2dly. For their <hi>Practice,</hi> I found therein no Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all; for ſome followed the Rules of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Bruno,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41796:29"/>ſome of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Kath rine,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Bridgit,</hi> ſome of St. <hi>Urſula,</hi> and ſo ſome of one, and ſome of another, the Rules of whom in very many things are quite contrary. Some again would have that our Lady was immaculate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived, and that the Pope is Infallible; otherſome will admit of neither. But perhaps the Papiſts will ſay, All theſe, together with the other before-mentioned, are, and were Matters of Practice, and not of Faith; but in all Matters of Faith (ſay they) we agree: But the plain truth of it is, they define all matters of Faith, to be thoſe wherein they agree: So that to ſay the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth agree in all Matters of Faith, is but to ſay they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in thoſe things they do agree in; and ſo do all other Churches.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly. As for Miracles, I conſidered they were not only pretended to be wrought by thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Turks, Heathens,</hi> and preſent <hi>Jews:</hi> And ſince I could ſee no reaſon why to believe the one any more than the other, (having never known any ſuch thing wrought amongſt them) this ſignified nothing at all to me. Beſides, I obſerved the Miracles pretended by the Papiſts, were in many Ages ago, if ever, wrought; and ſo many Ages after the prefixed time of their being wrought, before they were once related to be done, that they were greatly to be ſuſpected, as meerly feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I conſidered the multitude of the Papiſts, and here I concluded, That if this were a Mark of the True Church, both <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> (and <hi>Greeks</hi> alſo in time paſt) were to be preferred before them.</p>
               <p>Next I camy to <hi>Sery,</hi> in my Journey to which, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering again of the great Differences I had obſerved in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41796:30"/>Religion, and the ſeveral Reaſons each Nation gave, for each Particular in which they differed; and moreover finding they had all much to ſay for themſelves, that in all things I could not believe them all, and that I could not be of any one Community amongſt them all, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur ſome Cenſure from one or other, either of <hi>Hereſie, Schiſm,</hi> or both; I burſt forth into theſe words.</p>
               <p>Good God! in what a miſerable Condition is a Man in this Life, he that is an honeſt and well-meaning man, that would be, knoweth not what to be. He would be a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> but then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him. He would be one of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but then the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> the <hi>Melchits,</hi> the <hi>Mengrelians,</hi> the <hi>Georgians,</hi> the <hi>Armenians,</hi> the <hi>Maronits.</hi> the <hi>Jacobits,</hi> the <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> the <hi>Indians,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> the <hi>Centurians,</hi> the <hi>Nubins,</hi> the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> the <hi>Abeſſines,</hi> the <hi>Circaſians,</hi> the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> the <hi>Slavoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the Chriſtians of St. <hi>John</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Greek,</hi> a <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> a <hi>Melchit,</hi> a <hi>Mengre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> a <hi>Georgian,</hi> an <hi>Armenian,</hi> a <hi>Maronit,</hi> a <hi>Jacobit,</hi> a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> an <hi>Indian,</hi> or <hi>Christian</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> a <hi>Centurian,</hi> a <hi>Nubin,</hi> an <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> an <hi>Abeſſine,</hi> a <hi>Circaſian,</hi> a <hi>Bohemian,</hi> a <hi>Slavonian,</hi> or a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of St. <hi>John,</hi> or one of any, or of all (if it were poſſible) of the aforementioned; but then the <hi>Coftians</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Cofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> or in <hi>fine,</hi> he would be any thing ſo he might be a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> but then the <hi>Samaritans</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> but then the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Jews</hi> would condemn him. He would be an <hi>Eſſene</hi> or a <hi>Common Jew;</hi> but then the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Phariſee</hi> or a <hi>Saddu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cee,</hi> or in <hi>fine,</hi> he would be any thing ſo he might be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or a <hi>Jew,</hi> or both; but then the <hi>Turks</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Turk,</hi> or in <hi>fine,</hi> he would be either <hi>Jew, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but then the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41796:30"/>
                  <hi>Heathens</hi> would condemn him. He would be a <hi>Heathen,</hi> or in <hi>fine,</hi> either <hi>Chriſtian, Jew, Turk,</hi> or <hi>Heathen;</hi> but then the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> would condemn him. He would be an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> but then the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Heath us,</hi> and all the World would condemn him.</p>
               <p>In the next place therefore, ſhutting forth the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts,</hi> verily believing there was a God, (for indeed I could believe no other, for Heaven and Earth and all things therein ſhewed me as much,) I conſidered that though I could not believe them in all things all, in regard of their Diſagreement; yet in thoſe things in which they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, I had reaſon to do no other but to believe them all. I ſought therefore next to ſee in what they agreed, and finding they all agreed in theſe things and no other, <hi>viz.</hi> That there was a God, to be adored here; for which there was a <hi>Heaven</hi> for the Righteous, and a <hi>Hell</hi> for the Wicked, the one as a Reward, and the other as a Puniſhment for the fame hereafter: I concluded I had reaſon to believe them in theſe things, and no other. So that now I doubted even of Chriſtianity it ſelf. Next therefore being at <hi>Sery,</hi> there being a whole Pariſh of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in which there was three <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> all Prieſts, one of which ſeemed very Learned and Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I had a great deſire to have ſome Private Diſcourſe with him, And the better to have his Advice, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to Relate my Doubts, I went to him to Confeſſion; in which I declared, that by reaſon of my Travels, I had been brought even to doubt of the Truth both of Chriſt and Chriſtianity. The <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Father was greatly ſurpriſed to hear me relate this, and the better to regain me to the <hi>Faith,</hi> asked me, Whether I believed there was a God. I told him that that I did not only believe, but was very ſenſible of. He then asked me, Whether I believed the Holy Prophets, the Writers of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, were of God. To this I anſwered, I greatly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41796:31"/>queſtioned whether they were or no. He then ſhewed me divers Reaſons to prove they were of God, and that therefore, whatſoever was contained in their Propheſies, muſt needs be true: Which Reaſons, eſpecially thoſe which were moſt convincing to me, I have here inſerted, to wit, Firſt, That amongſt their Propheſies, many of which (foretelling things many years, and ſometimes Ages before they were to happen) being ſuch as in all probability, were never likely to come to paſs, nor could be conjectured by any Natural Cauſes, (as were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the things foretold by the <hi>Heathens</hi> and their <hi>Oracles</hi>) were notwithſtanding afterward moſt certainly fulfilled. As firſt, The Propheſie and Prediction made to <hi>Abraham</hi> of his Iſſue, when he had neither any, nor was ever like to have, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.16. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.2. <hi>Gen,</hi> 18.11, 12. Of his inheriting the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and above all of his Poſterities deſcent into <hi>Egypt,</hi> of their time of Servitude, and manner of deliverance thence; the ſame being foretold more than four hundred years before it was fulfilled, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13, 14. And when no likely hood thereof did at all appear, and yet how exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame was fulfilled, and at the very time appointed by the Propheſie, is declared in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.31, 32.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <hi>Jacobs</hi> Propheſie of the Kingly Government of <hi>Judah, Gen.</hi> 42.8, 9, 10. where there is mention made of his Brethrens bowing down to him, and withal of his Scepter; the Circumſtances whereof, if we ſeriouſly conſider, are exceedingly to be wondred at: For firſt, When theſe words were uttered by <hi>Jacob,</hi> there was no probability at all of any Scepter to be among the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> for they were poor and few in number, and never like to be a diſtinct Nation of themſelves, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part forth of <hi>Egypt</hi> again.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41796:31"/>
               <p>And 2dly. If any ſuch thing ſhould come to paſs, as that they might be a People, and have a Scepter of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their own; yet was it not that <hi>Judah</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity</hi> ſhould poſſeſs the ſame; for that he had three elder Brothers, to wit, <hi>Reuben, Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> who in all likely hood were to have it before him.</p>
               <p>And 3dly. When <hi>Moſes</hi> recorded and put in writing this Propheſie (which was divers hundred years after <hi>Jacob</hi> had ſpoken it) it was much leſs likely that ever it ſhould be true, in regard that <hi>Moſes</hi> then preſent in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was of the Tribe of <hi>Levi;</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> deſigned by God for his Succeſſour, was of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and not of <hi>Judah;</hi> which makes greatly for the certainty of this Record: For that it is moſt apparent, that <hi>Moſes</hi> would never have put ſuch a Propheſie in writing, to the diſgrace of his own Tribe, and to the prejudice and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Reuben, Simeon, Ephraim,</hi> and other Tribes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would they have ſuffered ſuch a Derogation, but that it was evident to them by Tradition, that their Grand-Father <hi>Jacob</hi> had ſpoken it; although then there was no great likely hood that ever after it ſhould come to be fulfilled. Nevertheleſs this was for the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereas if we conſider that from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> (that was the laſt of all the Judges) there paſſed four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years more, and yet was there no appearance of the fulfilling of this Propheſie in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for that the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> was not eſtabliſhed in that Government, it is the more to be wondred at. At length they came to have Kings to Rule, and then was there choſen <hi>Saul</hi> to the Place, who was not of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> but of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and he was endued with divers Children to ſucceed him; who therefore would have then thought that this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie could have ever been fulfilled? Nevertheleſs, when no man thought thereof, there was a poor Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd choſen out of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> called <hi>David,</hi> to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41796:32"/>be King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13. which Government of <hi>Judah,</hi> held out more than 1200 years together, even until the time of <hi>Herod, Euſeb. in Chron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly. The Propheſie of the ſame <hi>Jacob,</hi> for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Ephraim</hi> above <hi>Manaſſes, Gen.</hi> 48.19, 20. which afterward was fulfilled; for that <hi>Ephraim</hi> was always the greater and ſtronger Tribe, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 16. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 17. and became afterward the Head of the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or of the Ten Tribes, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 7.2, 9. whereof there was no ſuſpition or likely hood when <hi>Jacob</hi> ſpake this, or when <hi>Moſes</hi> recorded it.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly. The Propheſie of <hi>Moſes</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> forſaking of God, and of the many and great evils they ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur thereby, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.16, 17, 18. which afterward came to paſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly. The Propheſie of the Birth and Acts of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> more than 300 years before he was born, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.2. which afterward was exactly fulfilled, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.15.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly. The Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> of the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> and of the grievous Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould be in under them, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.17. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 5.26. As alſo the Deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> by <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia, Eſai.</hi> 13.1, 6. which Propheſie was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 200 years before the ſaid <hi>Cyrus</hi> was born; in which he declared his Name, and how (although a <hi>Heathen</hi>) he ſhould rebuild the City and Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem, Iſai.</hi> 44.28. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 45.1. which others of his own Religion had deſtroyed, all which accordingly came to paſs, and he nominateth two Witneſſes thereof, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Urius</hi> and <hi>Zacharias,</hi> which were not born of many years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the one being a Prophet in <hi>Jeremy's</hi> time, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.20. an hundred years after <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and the other eighty
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41796:32"/>years after that, in the days of <hi>Darius, Zach.</hi> 1. 1. This Captivity alſo was not only foretold by <hi>Jeremy,</hi> but firſt, The particular time how long the ſame ſhould endure. 2dly. The Deſtruction of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And 3dly. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home of the <hi>Jews</hi> again, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. all which was fulfilled accordingly, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 1. <hi>Neh.</hi> 3. And to theſe I might alſo add divers other things, all which being propheſied when there was not any likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood at all thereof, are a certain Proof, that theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (and others might be here mentioned) were of God, and their Writings were writ by Divine Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is a manifeſt Demonſtration of the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their Writings, and of the truth and certainty of what therein is contained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Second Reaſon he ſhewed me, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced me, was that many of the chiefeſt and ſtrangeſt things contained in the Scriptures were affirmed by the <hi>Heathens</hi> themſelves, (who though they differ ſomething from the Scriptures in the manner of their Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, yet do they thereby make the more for the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the things there mentioned, in regard that thereby it appears they took not their Hiſtories directly from the Bible, but Tradition and antient Antiquities of their own.) for Confirmation whereof, firſt he ſhewed me certain Writings of divers <hi>Heatheniſh Philoſophers,</hi> who ſpake therein of the Worlds Creation, and the infuſion of mans Soul from God. 2. The Writings of <hi>Beroſus, Abide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Chaldaeus, Damaſcenus, Egyptius, Nicholaus,</hi> and other moſt Antient Heathens, who mentioned the flood of <hi>Noah.</hi> 3. Of <hi>Heſiodus, Abdenda, Hecataeus, Ephotus, Accuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> and <hi>Helanicus,</hi> which teſtifyed that the firſt Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the World lived commonly a thouſand years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, which they ſaid was for Peoples Multiplication, and the bringing of all Sciences to Perfection. 4. Of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid nus, Heſtiaeus</hi> and <hi>Sibylla,</hi> who ſpake of the confuſion of Tongues at the building of the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi> 5. Of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polemus,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41796:33"/>who ſpeaketh of <hi>Abrahams</hi> being in <hi>Egypt,</hi> of his fight and victory in the behalf of <hi>Lot,</hi> of his Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> of his wife and Siſter <hi>Sara,</hi> and of the Sacrifice of his Son <hi>Iſaac.</hi> 6. Of <hi>Pauſaneus, Strabo, Tacitus</hi> and <hi>Solinus,</hi> wherein is made mention of the Lake of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> called the <hi>Dead Sea,</hi> wherein nothing can live. 7. Of <hi>Artabanus</hi> and <hi>Phylon,</hi> who have writ many things concurring with the Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning <hi>Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Joſeph.</hi> 8. Of <hi>Ariſtaeus,</hi> who hath written the Hiſtory of <hi>Job.</hi> 9. Of <hi>Eupolemus,</hi> who declares the wonderful things done by <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> for which (he ſaith) he was worſhipped as a God in that Country, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of <hi>Mercurius.</hi> And thus he went on from one to another, until he had proved the Truth of the whole Hiſtorical Part of the Old Teſtament, by <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Authors.</p>
               <p>This did exceedingly confirm me in the Truth of the Old Teſtament, but I deſired to know what this was to Chriſt and Chriſtianity. He then ſhewed me, firſt, how that Chriſt from time to time had been promiſed to the World as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Gen</hi> 26.4. <hi>Gen</hi> 49.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Pſal</hi> 89. <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.14. <hi>Eſai.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2 Secondly, the remarkable things which happened as concerning him which we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore for Chriſt, to wit, <hi>ifirſt,</hi> that he was born of a Virgin. 2. That he was born at <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> 3. That at his Birth all the Infants near <hi>Bethlehem</hi> were ſlain. 4. That that the wiſe men of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> came and adored him, and offered him Gifts and Preſents. 5. That he was preſented in the Temple. 6. That he fled into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterward was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called thence. 7. That a Meſſenger went before him to prepare the way for him. 8. That he did wonderful Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and healed all Diſeaſes. 9. That he was betrayed by a familiar friend, his Companion. 10. That he was ſold for <hi>thirty Pieces of Silver.</hi> 11. That with thoſe Thirty Pieces of Silver was bought the <hi>Potters Field.</hi> 12. That he rid upon an Aſſe to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 13. That the Jews did
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41796:33"/>beat and buffet him, and defile his face with ſpittle. 14. That they whipped and tore his Body before they Crucified him. 15. That they gave him <hi>Vinegar to drink,</hi> divided <hi>his Garments among them, and caſt Lots for his Vesture.</hi> 16. That he was Crucified in the Company of <hi>Theeves</hi> and <hi>Malefactors.</hi> 17. That he was refuſed and rejected by the Jews. 18. That until his coming the Scepter was not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Judah.</hi> 19. That from the building of the Second Temple unto the time of his Death, were Sixty two <hi>Heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domada</hi>'s. 20. That he was crucifyed by the Inhabitants in and about <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And 21. That immediately after his Paſſion the ſecond Temple was deſtroyed. All which (he told me) unleſs the firſt (and I knew it to be true) were acknowledged even by the Jews themſelves, and that alſo was acknowledged by the <hi>Turks.</hi> But then in the next place, I deſired to know of him, how theſe proved, that he whom we adored for Chriſt was the true Meſſias. He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that they proved it as plainly as might be; for all the things before mentioned, had been long before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of in the Old Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) That he ſhould be born of a Virgin, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 7.14. (2.) That he ſhould be born in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> Mic. 5.2. (3.) That at his Birth, all the Infants near <hi>Bethlehem</hi> ſhould be ſlain, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.15. (4.) That the Kings of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> (which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> by an Old Tradition of the Church, affirmeth in his Sermon of Baptiſm, were the <hi>Three wiſemen</hi>) ſhould come and adore him, and offer him gifts and Preſents, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.10. (5.) That he ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the <hi>Temple, Mal.</hi> 3.1. (6.) That he ſhould fly into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterward be recalled thence, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 19.1. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.1. (7.) That a Meſſenger ſhould go before him, to prepare the way for him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. (8.) That he ſhould do wonderful Miracles and heal all Diſeaſes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.5. (9.) That he ſhould be betrayed by a familiar friend, his Companion, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 41.9. <hi>Pſ</hi> 55.13, 14. (10.) That he ſhould be ſold for thirty pieces of Silver, <hi>Zac.</hi> 11.12, 13. (11.) That with thoſe thirty pieces of Silver ſhould be bought the Potters field, <hi>Zac.</hi> 11.12, 13.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41796:34"/>that he ſhould ride upon an Aſs to <hi>Jeruſalem, Zac.</hi> 9.9. (13.) That the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould beat and buffet him, and defile his face with Spittle, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 50.6. (14.) That they ſhould whip and tear his body before they crucifyed him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.2.7. (15.) That they ſhould give him Vinegar to drink, divide his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments among them, and caſt Lots for his Veſture, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.21. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.18. (16.) That he ſhould be crucifyed in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with Thieves and Malefactors, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.12. (17.) That he ſhould be refuſed and rejected by the Jews, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.22. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai.</hi> 6.9. (18.) That until his coming the Scepter ſhould not be taken from <hi>Judah, Gen.</hi> 49.10. (19.) That from the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſecond <hi>Temple</hi> until the time of his Death ſhould be ſixty two <hi>Hebdomada</hi>'s, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25, 26. (20.) That he ſhould be crucifyed by the Inhabitants in and about Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. (21.) That immediately after his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Second Temple</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25. And ſeeing they were all fully and perfectly fulfilled in him whom we thus adore; it was a certain, undoubted, and manifeſt truth, that this ſame Perſon was the <hi>True Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now being fully ſatisfyed in this, in the next place, I deſired to know of him, what he had to ſay for the Truth of Chriſtian Religion; he told me that the Truth of Chriſtian Religion manifeſtly appeared by the Miracles wrought by Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and other Saints, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it was confirmed and eſtabliſhed. I told him that I had heard the Jews ſay, that thoſe Miracles were wrote by Art Magick; He anſwered that the Miracles done by Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and other Saints, could not poſſibly be wrought by Art-Magick; for the greateſt Magicians upon Earth, ſeeking to imitate them, found it altogether in vain. <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> he ſhewed me, gave themſelves more to Magick than any that had ever been before them, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Emulation of the Miracles done in <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> when <hi>Nero</hi> lived, and by other Saints and Diſciples in the time of <hi>Julian;</hi> and yet were able to effect
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41796:34"/>nothing in that kind. <hi>Pliny</hi> he ſhewed me, that was a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> writeth thus of <hi>Nero;</hi> that as no man laboured more than he in the Art Magick, ſo no man ever left a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Teſtimony of the marvellous exceeding vanity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 30. <hi>Nat. Hiſt. cap.</hi> 1. The like in effect he ſhewed me, writeth <hi>Zozimus</hi> of <hi>Julian;</hi> though he himſelf was a malicious Heathen. <hi>Zoz.</hi> in <hi>vit. Julian.</hi> And if this ſame had not been written, he told me, yet their ſeveral extraordinary Calamities, and moſt miſerable Deaths, which by all their Magick they could not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, doth ſufficiently teſtifie the ſame to us; eſpecially the laſt words of <hi>Julian, Viciſti, Galilaee, vicisti,</hi> thou haſt overcome, O <hi>Galil an,</hi> thou haſt got the victory; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging thereby, as well the divine power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſt and his Followers wrought their Miracles, as alſo the folly, vanity, and madneſs of his own endeavours.</p>
               <p>And now (through my diſcourſe with this Fryar) I was more convinced of the truth of Chriſtianity, than with whatever before, I had either read or ſeen. And therefore rendring him innumerable thanks for what he had ſhewed me, I withal beſought him to tell me, which of all Chriſtian Churches he judged to be the beſt and trueſt. He told me the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I deſired his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; he told me the true Church was infallible, which none but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ever ſo much as pretended to be. <hi>That the true Church was infallible,</hi> he ſeemed to prove from <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. where tis ſaid <hi>when the Holy Ghost com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he ſhall teach you all truth;</hi> and from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. where tis alſo ſaid, <hi>The Church is the ground and Pillar of Truth.</hi> And that none but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ever ſo much as pretended to be ſo, I could not but acknowledg, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now I reſolved to continue in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And from thence, coming into <hi>Dalmatia, Bonifacio Albano</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Spolato,</hi> adviſed me to enter into Orders, made me <hi>Sub-Deacon,</hi> and after I had continued with him
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41796:35"/>ſome ſmall time (having a deſire to go into <hi>Italy</hi>) recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended me to the Grand Duke of <hi>Tuſcany;</hi> whilſt I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained with the Grand Duke, I went to <hi>Legorn,</hi> where I ſaw Biſhop JEWELL's Defence of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Willets</hi> three Centuries againſt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and obſerved that theſe their Writings were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to what I had read before in the Fathers.</p>
               <p>After this the Grand Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> recommended me to <hi>Cardinal Howard. Cardinal Howard</hi> promiſed to ſee me provided for, maintained me whilſt I ſtayed at <hi>Rome,</hi> cauſed me to be better inſtructed in the Ceremonies of Maſs, and deſigning me afterward for a Miſſion into <hi>England,</hi> procured me a Licenſe from the Pope, that I might read the Holy Scriptures in any Language I found them in.</p>
               <p>I no ſooner read the Holy Scriptures, but I greatly doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether or no any Adoration were to be given to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and fearing that their Adoration might be Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, or at leaſt wiſe diſpleaſing to Almighty God, I would when they were to be adored, as much as lay in me, continually avoid the ſame. And the rather in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I apprehended, that even the Moral Law, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves ſay is ſtill in force, did altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid any ſuch Adoration, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>All I found they had to ſay for the ſame, was in the underſtanding a rightly the Commandment; ſome would have it to forbid <hi>Latria,</hi> but not <hi>Dulia;</hi> other ſome to forbid <hi>Idols,</hi> but not <hi>Images;</hi> for ſay they, the word in the Original, is <hi>Peſel,</hi> and in <hi>Greek,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſignifieth an <hi>Idol;</hi> and to this they add, an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol</hi> is nothing, in regard it repreſents nothing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not to be adored, becauſe in its Adoration we dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it: whereas an Image, in regard it is a Repreſentative, is ſomething; and what Adoration is performed to it,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41796:35"/>redounds to the Perſon whom it repreſents, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore falls not under the notion of this prohibition.</p>
               <p>Upon this, I was fully reſolved, could I poſſibly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand where to meet with one, to ſpeak with ſome Jewiſh Rabbie; verily believing that ſince the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were firſt given to the <hi>Jews,</hi> he could tell me by their continual obſervance thereof ſince, in what Sence the ſaid command was given, and how Originally it was to be obſerved; but enquiring of certain <hi>Jews</hi> for ſome Rabbie, they fearing it was for ſome ill, durſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any one to me, ſo that for that time I was forc'd to let it reſt: nevertheleſs, ſome few days following I came to the ſpeech of one, without any difficulty, and that too by a meer accident, which was as followeth;</p>
               <p>Having a deſire to ſee ſome Remote Parts in <hi>Rome,</hi> which then I had not ſeen, I took my way toward <hi>Via Flumina;</hi> not far from which, ſeeing a great Multitude of People gathered together, I drew near to ſee what was the matter, and coming near them, I ſaw a Jeſuit preaching out of a Pulpit, Erected (a conſiderable height above the Peoples Heads) in the open ſtreet. All Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Goers, at leaſt-wiſe for a while, there ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and giving him an Audience; amongſt the reſt, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained alſo my ſelf a while, to hear his Doctrine: great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wondring, eſpecially in <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee ſuch an action performed in the open Streets, in regard it was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; where I had not loytered long, but I ſaw a great Multitude of <hi>Jews</hi> drawing near them, (which I ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed having been upon ſome occaſion or other at their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, were returning to their Habitations) which the Jeſuit alſo ſeeing, and knowing they muſt come by that way, gave a ſign to one who there attended him, for the Cruciſix; who fetching it out of a Houſe juſt by, brought it immediately to him, which the Jeſuit recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41796:36"/>in his Arms, turning his Diſcourſe altogether to the Paſſion of Chriſt, held up to be ſeen as the <hi>Jews</hi> were to paſs by; which was no ſooner thus held for view, but all the Chriſtians there preſent, fell down upon their Knees, bowing their Faces to the Earth to adore it; and the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtanding at a diſtance, and looking thereupon, laughed and grinned one to another thereat: and I for my own part to avoid its adoration took an Alley, where whilſt I loytered to ſee when it might be over, three of the ſaid <hi>Jews</hi> taking notice thereof, came to me into the Alley, and deſired to know of me whether or not I was well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in my Religion, I told them to ſpeak the truth, I was not very well ſatisfied with what I ſaw there, and that made me to avoid it, and take the Ally; they anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſo they perceived, and asked me if I had, a mind to ſpeak with one of their Rabbies; if I had they ſaid they would immediately help me to the ſpeech of one; I gave them thanks, and deſired they would; upon this they conſulted together ſome ſmall time, to know to whom they had beſt to bring me, which having concluded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they took me to <hi>Rabbi Salvator in via flumina;</hi> a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding well Learned, and of a very courteous, obliging Behaviour, who, having firſt privately acquainted him with the occaſion of their bringing me to him, leaving me with him, immediately departed. The Rabbie invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me to come in, and cauſed me to ſit down, after ſome ſmall diſcourſe with me, cauſed me to go with him into his Study; where deſiring to know of me, what it was in which I was diſatisfied, I told him <hi>I</hi> was diſatisfied in divers things, but the chiefeſt was the Adoration of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. And ſince the Adoration, or not Adoration of Them, depended altogether upon the Sence of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God given to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> upon Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, nor the likeneſs of any thing in Heaven above, or in the Earth beneath, Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41796:36"/>them, &amp;c.</hi> I deſired to know in what Sence both he and other <hi>Jews</hi> underſtood the ſame. He told me that in this Commandment, not only the Adoration of Images, but the very making of them with an intent to adore them, was Idolatry, and altogether forbidden. As for <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia,</hi> (he ſaid) they were humane diſtinctions, and had no Ground from Almighty God: I then argued, that this Cmomand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might forbid Idols, but not Images, and if ſo, the Adoration of Images was no doubt allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. He then asked me what both I and other amongſt us looked upon, to be the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt an Idol and an Image; I anſwered an Idol was a Thing adored as a God; whereas an Image was not a Thing adored as a God, but as a thing Repreſenting God; to this he ſaid, that an Idol and an Image (let the Image repreſent what it would) being adored, were the ſame thing. The which I not granting, he deſired to know of me, what the <hi>Golden Calf</hi> was, an <hi>Idol</hi> or an <hi>Image,</hi> That the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> for Adoration, cauſed <hi>Aaron</hi> to make in their Return from <hi>Egypt.</hi> I anſwered an Idol. He told me that unleſs I would grant that an Idol and an Image were the ſame thing, that was mine, and others miſtake; for what they adored then, they adored only as a Repreſentative. I deſired to know where he found that, he told me in one of the <hi>Pſal.</hi> &amp; ſhewed me the words, where 'tis ſaid, ſpeaking of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41796:37"/>the ſame People; <hi>That they turned their Glory</hi> (to wit the True God) <hi>into the likeneſs of a Calf that eateth Hay, Pſal.</hi> 106.20. So that (ſaid he) we did not Adore this Calf for a God, but for a Similitude Repreſenting God; and yet it was puniſhed by Almighty God for Idolatry, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. This did convince me very much, nevertheleſs I deſired for my further ſatisfaction that he would yet be pleaſed to give me, if he could, ſome other Teſtimony: he then ſhewed me how the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the other <hi>Jews,</hi> ſet up Two Calves, the one at <hi>Dan,</hi> and the other at <hi>Bethel:</hi> and how, notwithſtanding, they always afterwards adored them, yet they adored them not as Gods, but as Things Repreſenting God. This he proved out of <hi>Ezra,</hi> where 'tis ſaid, that when the <hi>Jews</hi> were permitted by King <hi>Cyrus</hi> to Rebuild their Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Samaritans</hi> came and would have joyned with them in the Rebuilding thereof, and would for the future have Adored at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but the <hi>Jews</hi> not permitting them, they would know the reaſon: <hi>why</hi> (ſay they) <hi>may we not build with you, we adore the ſame God that you do,</hi> Ezra 4.2. which (ſaid he) could not have been ſaid, had they Adored theſe Calves for Gods, and therefore they adored them not as Gods, but as Things on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſenting God. He Next made me ſenſible of the great Plagues and Puniſhments that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41796:37"/>God had often inflicted for this kind of Worſhip, all which could not but manifeſt his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great diſlike thereof.</p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe did ſo fully convince me, and brought me into ſuch a great diſlike of the Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Images, that I perfectly loathed all ſuch Adoration. And ſeeing thereby that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was fallible, and had erred in one thing, I believed it might have erred in more.</p>
               <p>And now it growing towards Evening, and the Rabbie being ſent for to reconcile ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that were fall'n out, (the Rabbies being, as far as I could underſtand, Judges in all ſuch Caſes) ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring him thanks for his good Inſtructions, I for that time took my Leave of him, who told me that at any other time, did I pleaſe to come to him, he would very willingly and gladly ſatisfie me in any other thing: Upon this I came to him ſeveral times afterwards, but all he convinced me of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, was,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1ſt. That there was no <hi>Limbus Infantium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2dly. That <hi>Saints, Angels,</hi> and <hi>Holy Reliques,</hi> were neither to be adored nor prayed to.</item>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:41796:38"/>
                  <item>And 3dly. that a very great part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion was perfect Magick: all which, with many other things, I deſign e're long to manifeſt to the world.</item>
               </list>
               <p>After this, being not very well in health, and feigning my ſelf much worſe than I was, I deſired leave of Cardinal <hi>Howard</hi> for change of Air to go into the Countrey, either to, or ſome where near <hi>Bologna;</hi> my deſign being to go to the Proteſtants, and having obtained the ſame of him, I was no ſooner taking order for my Journey, thinking therein to ſteer my Courſe towards ſome Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Country, but fearing the Inquiſition, being Purſued by certain Fryars, who reported they had often ſeen me in Company of the <hi>Jews,</hi> I immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, to prevent it, made an Eſcape by Sea to <hi>Naples,</hi> thinking from thence to get by Sea into <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being at <hi>Naples,</hi> ſeriouſly reflecting upon the many and great Friends I had then in <hi>Italy,</hi> and the great Probability I was in of coming there to very great Preferment, whereas if I went, I knew not whither, <hi>viz.</hi> to Proteſtants, to whom I was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unknown, I might be hardly looked upon, and perhaps too, when I came, diſlike their Practice, changing my reſolution, I reſolved to continue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41796:38"/>in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> From <hi>Naples</hi> therefore, croſſing the Countrey to <hi>Barlet,</hi> and ſo taking Ship for <hi>Venetia:</hi> and from thence going to <hi>Birgamo,</hi> get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome Letters of Recommendation to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop there, he preferred me into a <hi>Cannos</hi> Place, and made me a Deacon.</p>
               <p>And now I gave my ſelf ſeriouſly to the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures in which I had before made a conſiderable Progreſs; &amp; whereſoever I found they did not agree with the Faith &amp; Practice of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, I noted them down in a little Book; All which I found afterward did agree with what I had before obſerved in the Fathers. And revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſame to my Ghoſtly Father in Confeſſion, hoping thereby to receive ſatisfaction, he gave me ſuch weak and abſurd Anſwers, that I thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the farther diſſatisfied.</p>
               <p>And now I, again lamenting my hard Fate, that it was my Lot to have been brought up in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had a great deſire to ſee the Practice of ſome Proteſtant <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore pretending a Journey to <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> to ſee a Kinſman, who was lately arrived there from <hi>Ireland,</hi> furniſhing my ſelf with what Money and other neceſſaries I could for my Journey, I went for <hi>Geneva,</hi> purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſee the practice, and diſcourſe with them of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41796:39"/>the <hi>Geneva</hi> Church. And to the end I might do it the more ſecurely, I again put my ſelf into a <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> Habit, in which appearing at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Engliſh Man, the <hi>Clergy</hi> there never miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that I was a Proteſtant; and I being not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved what to do, told them no other, but that I having been, and then being, much among <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they continually preſſed upon me to be of their Church. And relating to them the ſeveral Arguments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which at any time before had ſerved me to retain me therein; I deſired their Inſtructions, how I might ſo anſwer them, as to defend my ſelf againſt them.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing, I deſired of them to make me capable thus to anſwer, was the Popes Infallibility, and leſt that ſhould not do,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. The Infallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. The Authority the <hi>Roman</hi> Church pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to have over the Scriptures, in Aboliſhing and making void part thereof at Her Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And 4thly. Her practiſing many things which were never mentioned in the Holy Scripture, for which She pretends Tradition.</p>
               <p>All, which ſeveral of them, anſwered ſo ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41796:39"/>rationally, learnedly, and diſcreetly, that I was exceeding well ſatisfied therewith, and returning them innumerable thanks, I deſired alſo to know of them what was the difference betwixt their own Church, and the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me, the difference betwixt Them and the Church of <hi>England</hi> was very little. The greateſt matter (they ſaid) was only <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and certain Ceremonies. This made me whilſt I ſtayed there, which was for the ſpace of a week or ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſeriouſly reflect with my ſelf what to do. And conſidering that their Service conſiſted moſt in Preaching, of which I was there very uncapable, in regard of my deficiency for the ſame in the French Tongue, I reſolved for <hi>England;</hi> not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but I might do God as good Service there, ſince the difference was ſo ſmall betwixt them, as here at <hi>Geneva;</hi> the which I ſhould immediately be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, in regard of my Engliſh Tongue. I was no ſooner ſetting out from thence towards <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> deſigning for <hi>England,</hi> but hearing I was near the Armies, and that in my direct way to <hi>Paris,</hi> I muſt upon neceſſity paſs them, which would be very dangerous: I was forced to retire to <hi>Lyons,</hi> where I was much further from <hi>Paris</hi> then I was at <hi>Geneva.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being at <hi>Lyons,</hi> having not ſufficiently left for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41796:40"/>my charge into <hi>England,</hi> my ſtock of moneys grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very low, I again began to alter my reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſtwiſe determined for a time, till I was in a condition for my Journey, to continue in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hoping Almighty God might accept of what I there did, ſince thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained thereunto: and ſo putting my ſelf again into a Clerks Habit, I hoped e're long to get an Employ. I had been there but a ſhort time, but Mr. <hi>Chapman</hi> an Engliſh Gentleman of <hi>Avinion,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Fargue</hi> a French Man, a Perſon of very good Quality, recommended me to the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; the Arch-Biſhop was pleaſed upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation to give me a Living, and to the end I might be the better qualified for the ſame, made me Prieſt. I now began to be in care how to defray the charges of my Inſtitution and Inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and other preſent charge and expences. And writing to a Friend at <hi>Birgamo,</hi> acqainting him that I had a Grant of a good Living in <hi>France,</hi> but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Money for my Inſtitution, Induction and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Neceſſaries, was willing upon reaſonable Terms to reſign my <hi>Canons</hi> Place there; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſiring him to help me to ſome Man that might take it of me; I had not expected long, but I received his Anſwer, in which he acquainted me, that if I would apply to one Monſieur <hi>Petite,</hi> who was a Shopkeeper in <hi>Lyons,</hi> he had received order
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41796:40"/>to agree with me for it. And coming to the ſaid Monſieur <hi>Petite,</hi> he gave me Twenty <hi>Lewie Dores</hi> for my Reſignation.</p>
               <p>And now I was in greater care than ever, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I thought to leave my preſent hopes, and to go for <hi>England:</hi> ſometimes again fearing that if I were there, I might have ſome diſlike, or at leaſt ſhould be altogether a ſtranger: and hearing that there was little or no Proviſion for Men who had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly done thus, but that divers who had turned to the Chruch of <hi>England,</hi> had been forced to turn from it again, meerly for a bare ſubſiſtance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to live: <hi>I</hi> was quite off it? but at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Celebration of Maſs was the dayly and in a manner only Practice of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy: <hi>I</hi> betook my ſelf ſeriouſly to read over the Maſs-Book: verily believing, that if my Conſcience could but diſpenſe with that, as for my Belief, <hi>I</hi> might the better diſſemble it.</p>
               <p>When <hi>I</hi> thus ſeriouſly read over the Maſs-Book, <hi>I</hi> found firſt, that ſome things therein were falſe, as the <hi>Introibo ad Altare Dei;</hi> for their Altar is not the Altar of God, but a meer Fiction of Men.</p>
               <p>And the Firſt and Ninth Part of the Canon, which ſay the Prieſt Kneeleth, when he Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41796:41"/>not: as alſo the <hi>Satiaſti Domine familiam tuam, &amp;c.</hi> wherein the Prieſt giveth us to underſtand, that the People have nothing at all.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. That otherſome were fooliſh, as the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi> for the Dead, wherein is prayed that God would remember ſuch as are gone before with the Sign of Faith, and ſleep in the ſleep of Peace, to grant them a place of comfort, of light, and peace. And the <hi>Amen</hi> ſaid after the Secrets adjoyned with the <hi>Per omnia Secula Seculorum</hi>'s: for how can the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay <hi>Amen</hi> when they heard nothing the Prieſt ſaid.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. That otherſome therein were Heretical, as the firſt Prayer in the Maſs for the Dead, and the Offertory: which gives us to underſtand that the faithful, departed, may be damned, and that ſuch as have believed and hoped, may ſuffer everlaſting Torments.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly. That otherſome therein where ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as the Prieſts ſometimes ſtanding, ſometimes ſtooping, ſometimes kiſſing, ſometimes croſſing, ſometimes joyning his hands and fingers, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times extending abroad his Arms, ſometimes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the one end of the Altar, ſometimes going to the other, and removing the Maſs-Book, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41796:41"/>turning his face to the People, ſometimes his back, ſometimes ſpeaking aloud as all may hear, ſometimes ſoftly as none may hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5thly. That otherſome were Blaſphemous, as the firſt Collect upon <hi>Ember-Wedneſday</hi> in <hi>Advent,</hi> which giveth us to underſtand that the Feaſt of <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> may give us the rewards of everlaſting bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The firſt Collect on <hi>Saturday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter;</hi> which prayeth that by our keeping of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> we may deſerve to come to everlaſting joyes. The Prayer at the offering of the Hoſt, which gives us to underſtand that the Hoſt not yet Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is profitable to the forgiveneſs of ſins, and Life Everlaſting. The Prayer for the fourth <hi>Ferie</hi> of the <hi>Ember</hi> days in <hi>Advent,</hi> the Tueſday af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Paſſion-<hi>Sunday,</hi> and the <hi>Friday</hi> in <hi>Ember</hi>-Week after the ſeventeenth <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> which gives us to underſtand that faſting may cleanſe us, make us worthy of Gods Grace, and bring us to the everlaſting Promiſes. A Prayer on the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty third <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Whitſuntide,</hi> which affirms, 1ſt. That God deſireth to be pleaſed by the Hoſts which the Prieſt offereth.</p>
               <p>And 2dly. That God would by thoſe Hoſts have ſafely reſtored to us the ſame, although not yet Conſecrated. The <hi>Memento</hi> for the Living, in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41796:42"/>which the Bread and Wine not yet Conſecrated, are offered to God for the Redemption of Souls. <hi>A</hi> Prayer which deſireth that God would accept the Bloud of his Son, the Redeemer of the World, as formerly he did the Bloud of the Beaſts. And the Conſecrations of Aſhes, Candles, Boughs, Cheeſe, Eggs, Bread, Fire, Frankinſence, Paſchal and Water, wherein is given to the Creatures, that which belongeth only to God and Chriſt, as the Power to forgive ſins, and to juſtifie and ſave.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly. That otherſome therein were Idolatry, as the Prieſts bowing to the Altar, his bowing to Holy Reliques hid in the Altar, and both Prieſts and Peoples Adoration of the Hoaſt and Cup.</p>
               <p>And 7thly. That otherſome therein were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, as the Charming of Water and Salt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the effecting of things by charmed Images, and charmed Bells, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, leaving my Friends and Fortunes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, I came preſently for <hi>England,</hi> where approving well of the Engliſh Church, I was at length (after great perſwaſions [by one accounted therein very eminent] to the contrary) reconciled thereunto; but was ſo long afterward before I got an Employ, that I was like to ſtarve. Some of the Clergy promiſing me that which they never did
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41796:42"/>perform; and others liking me the worſe for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over from the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſo that had it not been for ſome few certain perſons, they would have driven me (had it been poſſible) back again to the Papiſts. After this the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Counteſs of <hi>Feverſham</hi> (meerly out of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) gave me a little ſmall Vicarage, ſeveral of the Clergy then promiſing me in a ſhort time to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my condition, but they did it not. Since which the Court of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (notwithſtanding I was Legally Inſtituted and Inducted by the Dean and Chapter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and had peaceably at leaſt a year and half, if not more, enjoyed my Living) finding I had not had a Certificate of my ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Declaration, mentioned in the Act of Uniformity annexed to the Book of <hi>Common Prayer;</hi> (notwithſtanding my Legal Subſcription [in all reſpects] to the ſaid Declaration, and the vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy [both at my Inſtitution and Induction, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the three Months the Act allows in which to have the ſaid Cerificate] of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in which my Living was; ſo that there was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhop nor Ordinary [as the ſaid Act requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth] to give me ſuch a Certificate) did firſt ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate my Living, and afterward pronounce it <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void, not ſuffering me to come into my Church, or to receive from the ſame any benefit. So that now I am again like to ſtarve; (and in all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41796:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>bability had ſtarved e're this, had it not been for my Lord <hi>Rockingham,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lewis</hi> Rector of <hi>Benefield</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> and ſome few others, (whoſe late exceeding great favours ſhewn me, I pray God requite.) And what to do I know not: return to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I will not; dig I cannot; to beg I am aſhamed: and ſhould I (could I follow any other Employ) leave off the Miniſtry, I ſhould fall under the Laſh of one of the Canons of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And thus, notwithſtanding I have forſook the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> and (in all reſpects) conformed to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, I am in a ſtrait every way. In fine I cannot but wonder that the Blaſphemous and Idolatrous Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould have Colleges both at <hi>Paris</hi> and at <hi>Rome</hi> richly endowed for <hi>Perverts;</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> pretending to abhorre and loath Her, ſhould make no Proviſion, or afford in the leaſt any Employ to <hi>Converts.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:41796:43"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
